<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The vvay to life and death. Laid down in a sermon, 1629. before the Lord Major of London then being. / By N. Waker M.A. late minister of Jesus Christ at Lawndon in Buckinghamshire. Now published for the reasonableness of the advice therein given, touching the five controverted points, viz. predestination, general redemption, freewill, conversion, and perseverance of the siants. Directing a safe way for the practice of private Christians, as confessed by the disputants on both sides.</title>
            <author>Waker, Nathaniel.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1655</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 127 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 52 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A96627</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W281</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1639_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R209056</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99867961</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99867961</idno>
            <idno type="VID">170192</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A96627)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 170192)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 206:E1639[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The vvay to life and death. Laid down in a sermon, 1629. before the Lord Major of London then being. / By N. Waker M.A. late minister of Jesus Christ at Lawndon in Buckinghamshire. Now published for the reasonableness of the advice therein given, touching the five controverted points, viz. predestination, general redemption, freewill, conversion, and perseverance of the siants. Directing a safe way for the practice of private Christians, as confessed by the disputants on both sides.</title>
                  <author>Waker, Nathaniel.</author>
                  <author>Waker, John.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 96 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.L. for Phil. Stephens at the gilded Lyon in St. Pauls Church-yard.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1655.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Preface signed: J. Waker.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "August. 28".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Romans VIII, 13 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:170192:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE WAY To Life and Death.</p>
            <p>LAID Down in a SERMON, 1629. before the Lord Major of <hi>London</hi> then being.</p>
            <p>By <hi>N. Waker</hi> M. A. late Miniſter of Jeſus Chriſt at <hi>Lawndon</hi> in <hi>Buck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inghamſhire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now publiſhed for the reaſonableneſſe of the advice therein given, touching the five Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverted points, <hi>viz.</hi> Predeſtination, general Redemption, Freewill, Converſion, and Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance of the Saints.</p>
            <p>Directing a ſafe way for the Practice of private Chriſtians, as confeſſed by the diſputants on both ſides.</p>
            <p>The text, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.13. <hi>For if ye live after the fleſh, ye ſhall dye, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. L.</hi> for <hi>Phil. Stephens</hi> at the gilded Lyon in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard. 1655.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:170192:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:170192:2"/>
            <head>TO The Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hat entertainment this sermon will find in the World, I can eaſily fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee. Some I hope it will both profit, and delight. If it diſpleaſeth ſome others, I have what I looked for. To the pious, cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable, and ingenious, it cannot (I think) be unacceptable: ſure I am un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſonable 'twill never be: ſo long as the world is ſo full of walkers after the fleſh, the ſharpeſt reproof comes not amiſſe. Of the Authour, my near rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion forbids me to expreſſe what I
<pb facs="tcp:170192:3"/>might juſtly make known to the world.</p>
            <p>In the eyes of ſome he will be in diſlike, as being (in their opinion) too mild and moderate in the Controverſies about <hi>Predeſtination, General Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, Perſeverance,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Touching which Points, he layeth down the Rules for Chriſtian practice according to Godlineſſe; which are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed to be ſo by the Diſputants on both ſides. Live here we muſt, as if infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libly choſen to life eternall, and yet never ceaſe to <hi>give all diligence to make our calling and election ſure,</hi> implore the ſpeciall ayd, and aſsiſtance of his holy Spirit, who <hi>worketh in us both to will, and do, even all our works in us, and for us;</hi> not forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in the meantime to <hi>work out</hi> our own <hi>ſalvation with fear and trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Further, we have here a portraiture of <hi>LIFE and DEATH,</hi> the life of the ſpiritual, with the death of the carnal, both of them pictured and ſet
<pb facs="tcp:170192:3"/>forth in moſt lively colours, upon which is grounded a pious and patheti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Exhortation to faſting and mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, a duty as well now as then, yea, now (if ever) needful: A Plat-form we have drawn to our hands, by the Learned and moſt eminently holy Biſhop <hi>HALL:</hi>
               <note place="margin">In a Book entituled. The Holy Order and Fraternity of Mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers in Sion</note> Let none be aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to follow ſo worthy a guide; and have we not juſt cauſe? our ſins and Gods Judgments, the confuſion of our Land, the ruines of a fair and flouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Church, will not all this open the flood gates of our teares? yea, let it at laſt (till then there is no hope of mercy) wring from us bitter cryes and lamentations. Let us all with holy <hi>David</hi> ſet our faces unto the Lord God, to ſeek by prayer and ſupplications, with faſting, and ſackcloth, and aſhes, nor let us ever ceaſe till our God at length (overcome with our importuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty) ſhew mercy unto us, bind up the wounds of this bleeding Iſland, hear the prayers of thoſe that ſtand in the
<pb facs="tcp:170192:4"/>Gap, and be favourable unto us. All which that he would for his Sons ſake, hear, and grant, is the unceſſant pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of him who profeſſeth himſelf one of that Holy Fraternity of <hi>Spirituall Mourners.</hi> Even yours in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Saviour,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>John Waker.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:170192:4"/>
            <head>
               <hi>THE</hi> Way to Life and Death.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Rom. 8.13.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>For if ye live after the fleſh, ye ſhall dye; but if ye through the Spirit do mortifie the deeds of the body, ye ſhall live.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His whole Univerſe may not unfitly be divided into three principall Kingdomes;<note place="margin">The Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduction.</note> the firſt in Heaven, where God reigneth; the ſecond in hell, where Beelzebub domineereth; and the third on Earth, which God hath given to the children of men. In the firſt is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but holineſſe, and happineſſe; in the ſecond nothing but ſin and miſery; in the third a mixture of all: in the firſt is light without darkneſſe, in the ſecond
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:170192:5"/>darkneſſe without light, in the third both light and darkneſſe. In the firſt are An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, and the <hi>spirits of juſt men made per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect</hi> in glory and bliſſe; in the ſecond, the Devil, and his angels tormented in flames; and here are men of a middle condition placed on earth, for the tryal of their obedience; and accordingly, as they ſhall demean themſelves in this world, ſo ſhall their doom be hereafter, either to live with God, who is the fountain of life; or dye that ſecond death with the dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ſpirits. Here then we are in a center, from hence are drawen two long lines, the one reaching to heaven, the other to hell: in this world God hath ſhewed us the way of both; the one, that we might avoid it; the other, that we might walk in it; nay, he hath given us a taſte of both, of hell in the miſeries of the world; of heaven in the comforts of it; of this, that we might long for the fruition of the harveſt; of that, that ſo we might ever take heed, how we come into that place of torment. So then there are but two conditions after this life; the one of joy, the other of torment; the one of life, the other of death: and there are but two eſtates of life in this
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:170192:5"/>world, as meanes tending thereunto, one evil, another good; ſome live after the fleſh, and ſome after the Spirit; and they that <hi>live after the fleſh ſhall dye, but</hi> they that by <hi>the Spirit, do mortifie the deeds of the body, ſhall live:</hi> So that here the Apoſtle deſcribes two contrary waies, and two contrary ends unto which they lead, the firſt is the broad way that lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth to deſtruction, a way of pleaſure, but it endeth in woe. The voluptuous man now fares deliciouſly, anon cannot get a drop of water; now cloathed in fcarlet, anon tormented in flames; now accompanied with Nobles, anon haled by devils: the other ſowes in teares, but reaps in joy; now full of ſores with <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarus,</hi> anon with him full of pleaſures; now among the dogs, anon among An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels; now on the dung-hill, anon in <hi>Abrahams</hi> boſome, <hi>verè ſtupendae vices:</hi> the former of theſe wayes is through the faireſt ſtreet in the City, but it leads to the place of execution; the other through a narrow dirty Lane, but it brings to the Kings Palace, where is prepared a coſtly banquet; the firſt is a way pleaſing to fleſh and blood, ſtrewed with Roſes, over flowery meadows, having all the delights
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:170192:6"/>that nature, or art can afford, but it leads at laſt to the dead Sea, it tends to the chambers of death: the other is beſet with briars and thornes, haunted with wild beaſts, theeves, and robbers, over craggy Rocks, and ſteep Mountaines; where if a man cannot find a way, (for few tread that path,) he muſt make it, (as he did over the Alpes) but this way leads to the new Jeruſalem, to the Celeſtial Paradiſe; <hi>Non quà, ſed quò,</hi> muſt be the wiſe mans quaery, not which way we go, but whither: ſo that here you have our Saviours two men in the field, <hi>two wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men grinding, the one taken, the other left;</hi> you have his <hi>broad way, that leadeth to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction,</hi> the way of the fleſh, <hi>and many there be that walk that way;</hi> the other the <hi>narrow way, that leads to life, to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie the deeds of the body, and few there be that find it. For if ye live after the fleſh, ye ſhall dye, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which words (to avoid needleſſe cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioſity) admit of a threefold conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:<note place="margin">The words variouſly conſidered.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. We may conſider them abſolutely, and ſo they contain two conditional Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions;<note n="1" place="margin">Abſolutely.</note> the one, a Commination, <hi>If ye live after the fleſh ye ſhall dye;</hi> the ſecond,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:170192:6"/>a Conſolation, <hi>If ye by the Spirit morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the deeds of the body, ye ſhall live.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. We may note them in their <hi>anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſis,</hi> or oppoſition;<note n="2" place="margin">In their antitheſis.</note> 
               <hi>Though the wicked be deſtroyed, yet it ſhall go well with the righteous,</hi> intimated in the particle <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, but; and <hi>though the wicked periſh as dung, yee it ſhall go well with the righteous:</hi> and <hi>contrà:</hi> there is, and ever will be an op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition.</p>
            <p n="3">3. In their coherence, intimated in the illation <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which briefly lyeth thus:<note n="3" place="margin">In their coherence.</note> There are two things which moleſt a Chriſtian that is juſtified, the reliques of ſin, which he thinks cannot ſtand with Juſtification, and Sanctification; and the afflictions of this life, which ſeem re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnant both to the mercy, and Juſtice of God. The Apoſtle in this Chapter pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribeth an antidote for both, giveth both comfort, and counſel: for afflictions, the comfort is, that they ſhall work our good here, augment our glory hereafter; and the counſel inferred, therefore to be pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient under them, and make good uſe of them: for ſin, though it do remain, yet it ſhall not condemn, unleſſe it raign; that is the comfort, and his counſel; and therefore let it not raign, but mortifie it:
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:170192:7"/>and in this verſe he layes down a twofold Argument to incite Chriſtians, to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace that counſel; <hi>For if ye live after the fleſh,</hi> &amp;c. The firſt is taken from the pernicious conſequent of a carnal life, the ſecond from a ſweet effect of a ſpiritual: <hi>For if ye live after the fleſh, &amp;c.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt then to handle the words abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely, as two diſtinct conditional Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions,<note n="1" place="margin">Abſolutely conſidered, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> two parts, a Commi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on and C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> 
               <hi>If ye live,</hi> &amp;c. and here <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſum aliquid videtur docere divinus ſermo,</hi> Strange paradoxes to ſome <hi>Nico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demus,</hi> divine riddles like that of <hi>Samp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</hi> If we laugh now, we muſt weep hereafter; but if we <hi>ſowe in teares,</hi> we <hi>ſhall reap in joy;</hi> the way to death, is to live in pleaſure; the way to life, is here to dye. He that will ſave the life of his ſin, ſhall loſe the life of his ſoul; but he that mortifies himſelf, his moſt beloved ſelf, he ſhall live for ever.</p>
            <p>In the Commination, 1. <hi>Proponit mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum culpae,</hi> he layes down the kind of ſin, to <hi>live after the fleſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Oſtendit ſtipendium miſeriae,</hi> he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares the horrour of their puniſhment, <hi>Moriemini, Ye ſhall dye.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:170192:7"/>
            <p>
               <hi>In the Conſolation</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Proponit officium,</hi> he preſcribes a duty, that is, by the Spirit to mortify the deeds of the body.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Promittit mercedem,</hi> he promiſeth a reward; <hi>Ye ſhall live.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And firſt to begin with the Commina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, where are laid down two eſtates of the wicked; the one preſent,<note n="1" place="margin">Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>m<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination.</note> the other future; the one of pleaſure, the other of pain; neither of which the Apoſtle di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly chargeth on the Romans, but ſhews, that by admitting the former vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntarily, they involuntarily plunge themſelves into the latter. <hi>If ye live af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the fleſh, ye ſhall dye;</hi> where is the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of the diſpoſition and condition hereafter of every Epicure; yea, every un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regenerate man like that prodigal, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives his portion from his father, he feeds his eye, his ear, his palate; but with him never returnes to his father any more; but rather like the rich glutton, he goes clad in purple, and Scarlet, and fares deliciouſly every day, but at laſt he dies, and that death is but the beginning of death; when his friends leave him, the fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ends take him, and carry him to the place of torment.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:170192:8"/>
            <p>But before we can improve this for your ſpiritual advantage, we muſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicate the two things propounded, what the ſinne is, and what the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>The ſinne is to live after the fleſh; where two things offer themſelves to our view; 1. The rule (though a crooked one) that is the fleſh. 2. The confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity to this rule, which is nothing but ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regularity, to live after the fleſh: of which briefly.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt for the rule, The fleſh and the Spirit are two captaines under whoſe ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners all men in this world are combatants; theſe have divers lawes, and weapons, conſtant, and continual oppoſition, and a ſeveral reward. As for unregenerate men, they have the fleſh for their guide: now what this fleſh is you ſhall ſee.</p>
            <p>Sometimes it is taken for a ſubſtance; ſo it</p>
            <p n="1">1. Signifieth the nature of man, or all mankind,<note place="margin">Fleſh what it ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth.</note> 
               <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.12. <hi>All fleſh had cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted his way;</hi> in this ſenſe it is no ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, nor muſt we <hi>Timon</hi>-like be haters of men, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or for humane nature, <hi>Iſ.</hi> 40.6 ſometimes more ſtrictly it ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth the body, as oppoſed to the ſoul,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:170192:8"/>2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.1. in this ſenſe we muſt not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim enmity againſt our ſelves, nor like thoſe fooliſh Baalites hate, or hurt our own fleſh: or moſt ſtrictly for that ſolid and ſimilary part of the body, contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed to the blood, bones, nerves, and ſine wes, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 79.2. <hi>the fleſh of thy Saints unto the beaſts of the earth.</hi> It is inhumane, and barbarons for another to abuſe this, but unnatural for a man to do it himſelf, therefore this is not the meaning.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It's ſometimes taken accidentally, ſometimes in the better part, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 11.19. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. more uſually in the worſe; ſo it</p>
            <p>Signifieth the frailty of humane na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, an effect of ſin, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.50. in this ſenſe Chriſtians are in the fleſh. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.2, 3, 4. in this ſenſe it is no potent enemy, but a weak friend, not to be oppoſed with weapons, but comforted with cordials: or moſt uſually for ſinne, which is the cauſe of this frailty, that Leproſie which overſpreads the whole nature, mind, will, memory, ſenſes, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, body, and all; diſabling a man from that which is truly, and ſavingly good, and inclining him to every thing
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:170192:9"/>that is evil; the unhappy off-ſpring of our firſt Parents, the mother, and nurſe of all thoſe vipers that daily breed in our own boſomes, and that hereditary diſeaſe which we derive unto all our poſterity. By the way we muſt note, that not the body alone, as the <hi>Manichees</hi> dreamed, or the inferiour faculties onely, as our adverſaries of <hi>Rome,</hi> ſome of them ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, are termed fleſh; for we read of a mind that is carnal, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. the pureſt part of the ſoul; yea, the quinteſſence of that part, the <hi>intellectus agens,</hi> as ſome will have it, the <hi>Spirit of the mind,</hi> as the Apoſtle calls it, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.1. that muſt be renewed: therefore it ſignifieth that ſinful diſpoſition that is in the whole man. Therefore you muſt not here with the <hi>Manichees</hi> accuſe the nature of the fleſh; for he which praiſeth the nature of the ſoul as the chiefeſt good, and accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the nature of the fleſh, as an evil thing, loves the ſoul carnally, and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally flies the fleſh.<note place="margin">St. Auguſt. Lib. 14. de civit. Dei, cap. 5.</note> 
               <hi>Nam qui velut ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum bonum laudat animae naturam, et tanqùam malum naturam carnis accuſat, profecto animam carnaliter appetit, et car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem carnaliter fugit;</hi> and as he ſaith elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, The fleſh is not naturally repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:170192:9"/>to reaſon, but as vicious: <hi>Caro non repugnat naturaliter rationi, ſed ex vitio:</hi> and again, The corruptible fleſh makes not the ſoul ſinful, but the ſinful ſoul makes the fleſh corruptible: <hi>Caro cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptibilis non facit animam peceatricem, ſed anima peccatrix fecit eſſe corruptibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem carnem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now ſin is called by the name of fleſh,<note place="margin">Sin why called fleſh.</note> rather then any other part of man, it may be to caſt ignominy upon ſin, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe this is one of the groſſeſt parts, where is moſt earth, that is predominant, the baſeſt element; to ſhew the diſſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude and diſtance betwixt corruption, and the Spirit, he denominates it from that ſubſtance which is moſt unlike the Spirit; or becauſe many motions of it ariſe from the fleſh, are fomented by the fleſh, and tend to the pleaſing of the fleſh, and acted, and perfected by the fleſh; the fleſh is that oft-times which offers the bait to the ſoul, as the ſtomach or ſpleen, being troubled with oppi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, ſend fumes to the brain; or to ſhew how near corruption is unto us, as it were incorporated, nay, transformed into us, and we into it; and ſo much the more dangerous, becauſe it is a viper
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:170192:10"/>bred in our own fleſh, and harboured in our own boſome; or becauſe the ſoul in committing of ſin doth give over it ſelf to fleſhly delights. The ſoul while, and when it ſtill hankereth after fleſhly things is called fleſh, <hi>Anima verò dum carnalia bona adhuc appetit caro nominatur;</hi> and ſo in the perpetrating of ſinne, the ſoul is made ſubject to the fleſh, and as it were transformed into fleſh. St. <hi>Aug.</hi> renders another,<note place="margin">Ser. 48. de verbis Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini.</note> becauſe fleſh was a ſacrifice for ſinne, as Chriſt that knew no ſin, is ſaid to be made ſin, that is, a ſacrifice for ſin; whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in ſome, or in all theſe regards ſin is called by the nameof fleſh, I will not fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther diſpute. You ſee what is meant by this name, and thereaſon of the denomination. And ſo much for the rule, the fleſh.</p>
            <p>I come now to the conformity of this rule,<note place="margin">What it is to live after the fleſh.</note> which is indeed meer deformity, which is to live after the fleſh: it is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led a life, though indeed he that thus lives is dead while he lives, and becauſe fleſh, as we heard, is diffuſed thorow the whole man, we wil conſider it both in ſoul and body, what it is to live after the fleſh.</p>
            <p>In the mind and underſtanding, to walk according to the fleſh, is to give conſent to fleſhly deſires;<note place="margin">In the mind and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding.</note> 
               <hi>Secundum carnem am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulare
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:170192:10"/>eſt carnalibus concupiſcentiis con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentire, Aug.</hi> When the fancy runs in a muze of ſinfull objects with delight, and takes thought for the fleſh to fulfil it in the luſts of it, to ſearch out myſteries of iniquity, and prove wiſe to do evil, that in their judgement eſteem a ſinful life to be happy, and account it wiſdome with profane <hi>Eſau</hi> to ſell their eternal birth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right, to purchaſe this meſſe of pottage. There are in the mind of man a world of falſe principles, to harbour theſe, and to live after them, is to live after the fleſh. The fleſh is ſometimes a Devil to it ſelf, ſometimes provoked by the Devil his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments, and outward objects; as theſe and the like are the fleſhes Creed, That Religion is but a matter of policy, or a bare profeſſion of it ſerves the turn, or ſome Ceremonies and formalities; or to reſt in ſome duties, or avoid ſome ſins; that it is lawful to commit ſmaller ſins, to avoid great or imminent danger; that it is too much preciſeneſſe to make con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of ſmaller ſins, it is no ſin to abuſe liberty in things indifferent, to extenuate or hide ſin, that we may deferre our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance becauſe God is merciful, it per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwades that Chriſtian duties are tedious,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:170192:11"/>and not neceſſary, therefore not to do them at all, or elſe not preſently, or elſe not conſtantly, or elſe unſeaſonably, ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantly, or heartleſſely, or elſe to reſt in the work done, and grow proud of it, In holy Scripture there is a kind of wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome attributed to the fleſh, called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; Some tranſlate it pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, <hi>prudentiam;</hi> others underſtanding, <hi>intelligentiam;</hi> others affection, or deſire, <hi>affectum;</hi> others ſenſe, <hi>ſenſum;</hi> Now <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is a habit of acting according to right reaſon, in all things that are good or evil to man, <hi>eſt habitus agendi ſecundum rectam rationem circa univerſa bona vel mala homini;</hi> but this is carnal wiſdome, and our Saviour ſpeaks of ſome that in their generation are wiſer, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, they do meditate on earthly things, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, chuſe according to the fleſh, the world rather then grace, or heaven, fly the ſmoke, and fall into the fire; chuſe ſin rather then labour or ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, get earthly things rathen heavenly, carnal rather then Spiritual, temporal ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then eternal. This is fooliſhneſſe with God, and they live after the fleſh, that hearken to this counſel.</p>
            <p>In the will they live according to the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:170192:11"/>ſleſh,<note place="margin">In the will and affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</note> that are ruled by that perverſe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, which it bears to God and his Law; in the memory, that make it a treaſurie of wickedneſſe; in their affections, that ſet them upon wrong objects, or inordinate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and immoderately on the right, that love ſinful delights conſtantly; if they are abſent, deſire them, and greeve for them; if preſent, rejoyce and delight in them.</p>
            <p>In their lives, and actions,<note place="margin">In natural actions.</note> men live after the fleſh, that eat, drink, ſleep, &amp;c. not for neceſſity, but to ſatisfie luſt unſeaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nably, immoderately: thus in natural actions. So St. <hi>Aug.</hi>
               <note place="margin">De docu. Salut.</note> He lives accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the fleſh, who ſo lives according to himſelf, &amp;c. <hi>Secundum carnem vivit qui ſecundum ſeipſum vivit, pergit quò vult, dormit quando vult, &amp; quamdiu vult loquitur quae vult, &amp; cui vult, manducat, &amp; bibit, quando vult, &amp; quantum vult, ridet &amp; jocundatur turpiter inter quos vult, &amp; quando vult, poſtremò quicquid naribus ſuave eſt quaerit, quicquid tactui blandum, quicquid oculis delectabile, quicquid corpori ſuo jocundum exercet, &amp; ſequitur qualiter vult, &amp; quando vult, qui omnia licita &amp; illicita carnaliter vult;</hi> he that makes himſelf, his fancy, his luſt,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:170192:12"/>the rule in his actions, that goes whither he liſts, that ſleepes when he will, and as long as he will, that laughs, and ſports, talkes ſcurrilouſly, or obſcenely at any time, in any company, and gives the raines to his luſt to pleaſe his ſenſual ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite in all things, that deſires things both good and bad, according to the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption of his own heart. And if this be to live after the fleſh, we may ſee by the fleſh of many, what it is they live af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
            <p>In civil actions that make their luſt a law;<note place="margin">In civil acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</note> that Magiſtrate that uſeth his ſword, or any Superiour his authority for his own private ends, in diſtributive juſtice; in inferiours when they deſire dignities, eat and drink, and curſe <hi>Abimelech,</hi> walkers after the fleſh, when they are full they deny God, much more his Miniſters; an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>archy is that they affect, that every man might do that which is right, yea, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times wrong in his own eyes; and if the Magiſtrates proceedings parallel not with their fancies; <hi>their tongue is their own, who is Lord over them?</hi> Jude 8. <hi>Michael</hi> durſt not revile the Devil, they ſpeak evil of the gods; in commutative juſtice, oppreſſe, defraud, and grind the faces of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:170192:12"/>the poor, ſo they can carry it ſmoothly, care not what they do; and ſo there be too too many, that caſt off all obedience in Political, Eccleſiaſtical, Occonomical Societies.</p>
            <p>In ſpiritual actions many live after the fleſh;<note place="margin">Matth. 23. In ſpiritual actions.</note> for not onely Epicures are guilty here, but an abſtemious Phariſee, that faſts twice a week, that placeth the power of godlineſſe in outward formalities; ſo our adverſaries of <hi>Rome</hi> when they moſt abſtain from fleſh, live after the fleſh; preferring ſometimes their own traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to Gods oracles, and ſometimes cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtantial parts of his worſhip to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantial, macerating their bodies, while they mortifie not their ſin. Nor can all amongſt our ſelves exempt themſelves here, right Formaliſts, I would they could ſee this beam in their eye, pray over beads many do; ſo ſome preach, and moſt hear, rather by tole then weight.</p>
            <p>Others placing their Religion in nice ſpeculations, zealouſly ſtriving for they know not what. Once it was a character of a Chriſtian almoſt among ſome to be repugnant to Church-Government, or at leaſt to diſobey with the heart; and
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:170192:13"/>deride with the tongue, what the hand had ſubſcribed to. But now that ſpirit is well laid, they have a new Creed which they are no leſſe hot for, though they underſtand it leſſe; and they are out of charity with that man, and will cenſure him for an Apoſtate, that is not to an haires breadth of their conceit, when it is indeed but a meer conceit.</p>
            <p>Others undertake acts of Religion with a carnal mind, and a corrupt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience for baſe ends, that preach for lucre, ſo did <hi>Judas;</hi> and pray for credit, ſo the Phariſees; that read for profit, like <hi>Diana's</hi> Chaplaines, and communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate for applanſe, and hear for all ends, do all for cuſtome, rather then con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and were it not for his own ends, would never longer ſerve that God which he cares not for. Of all walkers after the fleſh, the hypocrite is ſure to dye, for hell was chiefly prepared for him, and others are ſaid to have their portion with him.</p>
            <p>Now that in any of theſe kinds a man live after the fleſh, it is required,</p>
            <p>That there be an habitual purſuit of ſin, <hi>Carnem tanquam ducem ſequi;</hi> or as <hi>Salmer: Imperio, legibus, &amp; carnis deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deriis
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:170192:13"/>ſubeſſe.</hi> A man may ſometimes be drawn aſide by the fleſh, and yet not live after the fleſh; as <hi>Noah</hi> in his drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſſe, <hi>Lot</hi> in his inceſt, <hi>David</hi> in his adultery: as on the contrary you may ſee <hi>Cain</hi> ſacrificing, <hi>Saul</hi> among the Prophets, <hi>Herod</hi> hearing <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> gladly, and ſtill living after the fleſh: as a paſſenger ſometimes wanders out of the way, and a thief ſometimes ſteps into it. To <hi>live accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the fleſh,</hi> intimates a conſtant courſe of mans life, that makes the law of ſin the rule of his obedience; they act this with moſt vigour, as from an inward principle. A wicked mans education, company, &amp;c. may ſometimes reſtrain from ſin; vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of temptation drives a good man upon it, but this is not their rule. <hi>Hieron. Omne quod loquimur, agimus, cogitamus, duobus ſeminatur agris, carne, et ſpiritu.</hi> Let us then examine the habitual courſe of our life, that is it which denominates, <hi>and if we live after the fleſh we muſt dye.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It were as poſſible to number the ſtars, to count the duſt, as to particularize the many luſts of the fleſh; mens converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions give us too many inſtances. I paſſe then from the ſinne to the puniſhment, <hi>Ye ſhall dye.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:170192:14"/>
            <p>We ſee what it is to live after the fleſh; and is not this a merry life, to go clad in purple, in ſcarlet, and fare deliciouſly every day, to neglect God in heaven, and contemne <hi>Lazarus</hi> on earth, to forget our ſelves whence we are, or whither we go? Yes, but hear what followes. The bell toles for this voluptuous Epicure, the earth that inſatiable grave longs for his corpulent carcaſe to feed wormes, and the devills ſtand waiting more eagerly for his ſoul. The Spirit of God hath writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten his doom in letters of blood, which with <hi>Belſhazzar</hi> might make his heart ake, and joynts tremble. <hi>Ye ſhall die.</hi> His pleaſure is gone, his guilt remains, and his damnation ſleepeth not. God wills not, yet he threatens death, <hi>Non vult mortem Deus, et minatur mortem;</hi> and therefore doth threaten it, becauſe he doth not deſire it, as willing to be prevented.</p>
            <p>You ſhall die,<note place="margin">What is here meant by death.</note> and what is that? How ſhould that be defined which is onely a privation? or if it had a poſitive being, how ſhould I deſcribe it, who never con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſed in thoſe Cells of darkneſſe, or with any that brought news from thoſe <hi>Cim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merian</hi> regions? or how can that diſtinctly be known, which contains in it nothing
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:170192:14"/>but confuſion, and contradiction, fire without light, burning, and no conſuming, labour in continual idleneſſe, living, and yet ever dying? for they live for nothing elſe, but that they may continually dye.</p>
            <p>If I ſhould procure you a painter to decipher the firſt death, he would ſhew you a grim anatomy, with a lean body, a pale face, a wanne countenance, &amp;c. that which hath devoured the whole world ſo many times over, like <hi>Pharaohs</hi> lean kine, is as lean as ever.</p>
            <p>And had you a Poet to deſcribe unto you the ſecond death, he would tell you of that <hi>triceps Cerberus,</hi> devouring the fleſh of the wicked; he would tell you of the two Rivers <hi>Cocitus,</hi> and <hi>Phlegethon,</hi> the one overflowing with tears, and the other boyling with brimſtone; they would make a narration of that <hi>palus Sty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gia,</hi> of <hi>Tantalus</hi> his apples, and <hi>Titius</hi> his liver devoured by vultures, of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual turning of <hi>Ixions</hi> wheel, and the rolling of <hi>Siſiphus</hi> his ſtone, or of thoſe infernal Furies, ready to torment thoſe whom <hi>Charon</hi> ſhould waft over; and <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentem dicere verum quis vetat?</hi> even theſe mythological expreſſions hold ſome pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:170192:15"/>with the truth. But I will draw my water out of a purer fountain; ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly it muſt needs be an ill-favoured brat that is born of two ſuch hideous Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, the Devil the father, and corrupt nature the mother; it muſt needs be ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible that is the wages for ſuch work ſo contrary to God, and goodneſſe.</p>
            <p>Death is nothing but a privation of life, and a ſubjecting the creature to thoſe miſeries, which are contrary to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts of life. And by life we do not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly underſtand the conjunction of ſoul and body, but all that perfection, and bliſſe, which was either actually conferred unto man, or to be communicated to him; ſo that in this monoſyllable is contained the whole world, hell with all the torments of that, earth with all the miſeries therein. But is there any death in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven? Surely it is a death to loſe heaven, and it contains that alſo; ſo that look how variouſly ſin reflects on God, ſo do his judgments on us, that we may read our ſin in the judgment.</p>
            <p>But that I may proceed orderly, I will borrow a diſtinction of <hi>Philo,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lib. leg. alleg.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:170192:15"/>There is a death of the man, and a death of the ſoul; the firſt is a ſeparation of ſoul and body; the ſecond a deſerting of vertue, and aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of ſin. But all miſery is called by the name of death, becauſe of all, death is moſt unavoidable, moſt bitter.</p>
            <p>Death in regard of the kind is either corporal, or ſpiritual,<note place="margin">Death Corporal. <hi>Sen.</hi>
               </note> which kinds are to be conſidered in degrees, inchoation,<note place="margin">In regard of inchoa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> and perfection; both which kinds are to be conſidered in regard of loſſe, and pain: <hi>You ſhall dye,</hi> that is, a corporal death, in regard of inchoation; for in this we are miſtaken, that we look forward upon death, whereas a great part of it is alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy paſt; <hi>in hoc enim fallimur, quod mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem prospicimus, magna pars ejus jam prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriit.</hi> Death is behind us a great part of it; the life of to day is the death of yeſterday. We dye daily. Every little publick, or perſonal croſſe, is a petty death, and a harbenger ſent by that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatiable enemy of humane nature to take poſſeſſion of his right. Thus you ſhall loſe the good temperature of body in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly, and outwardly all thoſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts of nature, whereby life is maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed;
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:170192:16"/>in a word, true dominion over the creatures, that in regard of loſſe: Either you ſhall loſe the world, or have it with a curſe, your table ſhall become a ſnare; and ſo ſome even dye with laughing, with a pleaſant gale of wind are carried upon rocks and ſands, pampered in fat paſtures for deſtruction, and carried down the pleaſant River <hi>Jordan</hi> into the Dead Sea. In regard of ſenſe, inwardly ye ſhall be perplexed with grief, and ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, and wearineſſe: outwardly, with famine, peſtilence, ſword; both wayes, with ten thouſand calamities, as waves of the Sea coming in the neck one of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, which as they be vexatious in themſelves, ſo certainly ſhall they be unto you; inſomuch that your life ſhall be an hard apprentiſhip, groaning daily under the iron yoke of bondage.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ye ſhall dye,</hi>
               <note place="margin">And Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> that is, a natural death, in regard of conſummation. This inexo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Sergeant that rides on the pale horſe, will ere long knock at your door, and by violence pull your ſoul out of that Tabernacle of clay, when the ſoul ſhall be kept in chaines of darkneſſe, till the judgment of that great day, and the body in the grave, as in a loathſome
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:170192:16"/>dung-hill, till that general Aſſize. In regard of loſſe here is a deprivation of life, and all that ſupports it, meat, drink, apparel, ſociety, and all the comforts of nature; and though there be no <hi>poena ſenſûs</hi> in the body which is kept in that hideous priſon, yet there is in the ſoul;<note place="margin">Luk. 16.25.</note> for the glutton cryes, <hi>Crucior in hac flamma;</hi> nay, and it may be this accur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed corporal death will take you away in the acting of your ſin, with <hi>Zimri,</hi> and <hi>Coſbi,</hi> ſo that you ſhall not live out half your dayes, but be haled to execution, as ſoon as your crimes are committed; and it may be before you go, feel the very flames of hell in your ſoules, as <hi>Cain</hi> and <hi>Judas</hi> did.</p>
            <p>But this natural death of the body though horrid unto nature,<note place="margin">Death ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual, in regard of inchoation.</note> yet it's no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to the ſpiritual death of the ſoul; that being a more excellent creature, and having a more eminent life. To proceed then, that is ſpiritually, in regard of inchoation, God ſhall be ſeparated from your ſoul, the light of his countenance ſhall not ſhine upon you, the underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing being full of darkneſſe, the heart of uncleanneſſe, the conſcience void of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renity, the whole ſoul out of order, full
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:170192:17"/>of confuſion, deſtitute of true com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort.</p>
            <p>In regard of ſenſe, a ſervitude and ſubjection of the ſoul to your ſpiritual enemies, and the powers of darkneſſe, made a vaſſal unto Satan, who worketh effectually in ſuch a ſlave to the world, which is the devils ſlave, yea, unto ſin, which is worſe then the world or the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil. In which regard it comes to paſſe, though a man retain that natural liberty of his will, which is eſſential to it, and cannot be loſt, yet that liberty which pertaineth to the perfection of humane nature to exerciſe acts ſpiritually good, and ſo ſavingly acceptable unto God, this is utterly loſt, man being dead in ſins and treſpaſſes, and the uncircumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of his heart.</p>
            <p>But all theſe are but the beginnings of ſorrowes;<note place="margin">And of conſumma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or eternall death.</note> that which is here principally meant, is the conſummation of ſpiritual death. And now had I but the keyes of hell, and death, to ſhew unto your bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily eyes a glimpſe of that infernal fire, and thoſe hideous monſters that dwell in thoſe horrid vaults, I ſhould either loſe my auditory, or it may be ſo prevail with ſome, that they would beware how they
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:170192:17"/>came into that place of torment. But I deſire that my ſpeech may work in you ſuch fear of thoſe paines, that you never feel them; and that you may be terrified ſo now, that hereafter you may be ſecure; conſider what <hi>Abraham</hi> ſaito to the rich glutton, <hi>Son, remember.</hi> We likely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member it not till it be too late, and therefore ſmart for it, becauſe we do not remember it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>You ſhall dye</hi> then, that is, firſt imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately, when your ſoul and body are parted, your ſoules ſhall be haled by the Devil into that place of torment. St. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt.</hi> ſpeaking of the rich glutton, ſaith, The ſoul likewiſe grieves when ſeparate from the body; for verily the rich man grieved in hell, when he ſaid, I am tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented in this flame. <hi>Dolet etiam anima non in corpore conſtituta, nam utique dole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat dives ille apud inferos, quando dicebat, Crucior in hac flamma.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And not onely with preſent torment, but with fear and expectation of future; his caſe is like to a condemned malefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors, who is adjudged to live two or three years under the place of execution, the gallowes, and all thoſe inſtruments of death continually in his eye, in the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:170192:18"/>mean time he is bound with chains, whip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped with Scorpions, fed with the bread of affliction. Thus he is moſt exqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitely tormented with pain of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, and horrour of that future venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance that is likely to fall upon him. So the divels cry out, <hi>Torment us not before the time.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But this is not all. The dregs of this cup of vengeance are yet behind. <hi>You ſhall dye,</hi> that is, your bodies, at that dreadful day, with the ſound of the Trumpet ſhall be awaked, like a Traytor to be brought before the Judge, and ſhall hear that doleful doom, <hi>Ite maledicti,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Go ye curſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now the loſſe here ſhall be unſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able;<note place="margin">In regard of loſſe.</note> He ſhall loſe God, and that loſſe is infinite, becauſe he is an infinite good, not in regard of his power, for that will be ever preſent to torment him; but in regard of the light of his countenance, that ſhall never more comfort him;<note place="margin">Mat. 25.41.</note> here is a total deſertion, and a final excluſion from his preſence:<note place="margin">Chryſ.</note> Should any one ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe 1000 hells, it will not be ſo much as to be driven from the happineſſe of this beatifical glory; <hi>Si mille aliquis ponat gehennas, nihil tale dicturus eſt, quale eſt,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:170192:18"/>à beatae illius gloriae honore repelli.</hi> Oh what Tophet is not a Paradiſe, what flames are not a bed of down to this? that that God who is the comfort of our ſoules, that wiſheth, and intreateth us now to be reconciled, ſhall then ſhut up his tender mercies in eternal diſpleaſure; <hi>Ite maledicti,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Go ye curſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again, there ſhall be a total privation of all the gifts of the Spirit, charity, peace, wiſdome, piety, mercy, and all the meanes that tend thereunto, Word, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, &amp;c. But it may be they will like the loſſe of theſe.</p>
            <p>In the next place, there ſhall be a loſſe of the world, and all the pleaſure of that; therefore St. <hi>Aug.</hi> notes, that <hi>Abraham</hi> ſpeaks to the rich man of good things paſt, <hi>Omnia dicit de praeterito, Dives erat, epulabatur, recepiſti.</hi> No meat, nor drink, cloathing, company, houſes, not ſo much as a drop of water to cool thy tongue.</p>
            <p>Nay, which is ſtrange, their very ſins they ſhall loſe ſome of them; thoſe ſins which delighted them they cannot com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, no adultery, or laſciviouſneſſe, no drunkenneſſe, gluttony, and revellings no Play-houſes, or brothel-houſes there,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:170192:19"/>but thoſe ſins which ſhall torment them, they ſhall be ſuffered to commit, if God withdraw the light of his countenance. Wicked men can comfort themſelves with the creature now; or if the creature de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny them ſolace, Gods people can encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage themſelves in God: but when both God and the creature are loſt, what com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort can there be?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>You ſhall dye.</hi> In regard of ſenſe in hell,<note place="margin">In regard of ſenſe.</note> a total, and eternal bondage of the whole man, when ſoul and body being re-united, both ſhall be caſt into that Lake of fire and brimſtone, where the body ſhall be terrified in all the ſenſes, in all the parts, outer darkneſſe to the eye; for there are flames, but no light; heat, but no comfort; to the ear howl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of tormented ſpirits, <hi>weeping, and wailing, and gnaſhing of teeth;</hi> to the ſmell, a ſtench of brimſtone, the very dregs of Gods wrath; to the feeling, exquiſite pain by fire. There ſhall be teares in the eyes, for there is <hi>weeping, and wailing;</hi> horrour in the eares, curſing, and complaining; brimſtone to torment the tongue, hands and feet bound with chains, fire to torment the whole body; but Oh forlorn wretch! hear more terror yet.</p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:170192:19"/>
            <p>But the moſt exquiſite pain ſhall be in the ſoul, becauſe that is the fountain of ſin which being infinitely abhorred by God in his wiſdome he will find out, and by his power execute ſome grievous pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment on it, and this is termed fire; a fire proportionable to a Spiritual eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, if not in the nature of it, yet by the ſupernatural power of the revenging Judge; exalted to a height of tranſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent efficacy: and the ſoul though in the nature of it immaterial, yet made paſſible by the power of a revenging Judge, that noble celeſtial ſubſtance, for ſubjecting it ſelf willingly to brutiſh ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuality, ſhall be unwillingly ſubjected to a ſenſual pain; this pain is the more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite, being principally in the ſoul; that diſeaſe tormenteth moſt, which ſeaſeth upon the ſpirits. <hi>Cain</hi> that felt but one ſpark of this fire was a perpetual vaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bond. <hi>Judas</hi> ſo tortured, as to hang himſelf, when he did but taſte of this cup. Oh what will their torment be, that drink the very dregs of this cup! and live in the midſt of theſe flames! Now the <hi>intellect</hi> ſhall be perplexed with the continual meditation of this, mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that happineſſe is loſt through her
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:170192:20"/>own default, and gnaſhing the teeth, that others have it, and the ſoul ſhall not chuſe but reflect upon it ſelf, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold her deformity and torment; and ſhall have nothing to drive away this meditation. The <hi>intellect</hi> ſhall repreſent this unto the will which ſhall hate it ſelf, and curſe God, that doth cauſe it to be captivated in thoſe chaines of darkneſſe; ſo that the ſoul ſhall for ever be a bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then to it ſelf, deſire that it were annihi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated, and hate God that ſupports her in being; the memory, which is the ſouls ſtorehouſe, ſhall continually reflect unto the conſcience, the cauſe of all this miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, with a <hi>Fili recordare,</hi> which ſhall be as a worm continually gnawing; ſo that the ſoul ſhall hate God who caſt it into that place, and the Devil that torments it in that place, and all the infernal ſpirits which add unto its torment; and the bleſſed Saints and Angels, which are in a better place, as an unthrift lookes out at priſon-grate upon men at liberty, and the body, as a companion of ſin and wo, and it ſelf who through her own default is brought unto that place, and by all ſhall be brought to thoſe exigences, which no tongue of man, or Angel is able to relate.
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:170192:20"/>
            </p>
            <p>But that which makes all compleat, this ſhall be eternal; heaven and all comfort are irrecoverably loſt, and the worme dieth not, though this puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment cannot be infinite intenſively; for then it would annihilate the creature be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing finite, yet in regard of duration it's in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite, that ſo ſatisfaction may be made to an infinite juſtice. If the lives of all crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures were added together, and ſpun out into one, and at the expiration of that there might be an end of their torment, it were ſome comfort. Were they to expiate their ſins with an Ocean of tears; and yet but every thouſand year to ſhed a tear, the debt in time would be diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged: And though this be an uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivable time, yet it would comfort a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, if then there might be an end, or a mitigation of the torment; but here the worm dieth not, the fire never goes out, here death ever lives, want knows not how to be deſective, the end ever beginneth, and death (which we now ſo fear as <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the moſt fearful of all other fearful things; for it is indeed the king of fears) will they then deſire as a Paradiſe, but it will fly from them, and that ſecond death will feed on them as
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:170192:21"/>graſſe, which ſuffers a continual death be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing cropt by the cattel, and yet ſtill lives in the root. If God preſerve the three children in the flames that they be not burnt: if mount <hi>Aetna</hi> ſends forth fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes continually, and it is not conſumed. Its St. <hi>Aug.</hi> argument, If the Salaman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der live perpetually in the fire, why can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not he by his power ſupport their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to live for ever, that they may ever dye? Oh how much better were it for them that they had never been, or as they had lived like beaſts, ſo they might die like beaſts, to be no more. So we ſee the conſolations of the fleſh, are the deſolations of the ſoul, <hi>Carnis con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolationes ſunt animi deſolationes.</hi> Hell ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver reſtores thoſe whom it once receives, <hi>Infernus, quos ſemel recipit, nunquam re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituit,</hi> ſaith <hi>Caſſiod.</hi> So <hi>Aug.</hi> ſins are bound, and looſed here, in the world to come is nothing but remuneration, and condemnation, <hi>Hic ligantur, &amp; ſolvuntur peccata, in futuro ſeculo nihil eſt niſi remu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neratio, &amp; condemnatio;</hi> no end, no eaſe, no intermiſſion.</p>
            <p>And thus you have heard the reward of the wicked, and the fearful doome o them that live after the fleſh. This is
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:170192:21"/>the cauſe why the man is deprived of comfort, and filled with ſorrow in this world; why the ſoul is deprived of God in ſpiritual death, and the body of the ſoul in corporal: this is the reaſon why the ſoul is deprived both of God, and the world from the natural death to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, and why both ſoul and body are deprived of the viſion and fruition of God to all eternity. Nor muſt you think this to be a meer fable, or Poetical fiction, or that we make the matter worſe then indeed it is; the ſingular purity of God cannot abide ſin, therefore it muſt be purged by blood or fire. God will have his juſtice magnified, therefore will not ſpare an onely Son; he will have truth maintained, who often hath declared this in his Word; its an irrevocable decree that they, <hi>who live after the fleſh ſhall dye.</hi> In the firſt decree, he ſaid to <hi>Adam, Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riemini,</hi> but his goodneſſe reverſed it; to <hi>Nineveh:</hi> Ye ſhall be deſtroyed, but yet upon their repentance ſpared, and ſo may theſe; elſe know this is a branch of the ſecond Covenant which ſhall not be abrogated. For what can God give bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then his Son on his part? or upon what eaſier termes can he capitulate
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:170192:22"/>with us? His wiſdome hath thought meet, that there ſhould be ſom bounds to his mercy, elſe he ſhould ſeem prodigal of it, and be thought to have abſolute need of his creature: and therefore not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding Chriſt his ſatisfaction to declare his juſtice againſt contemners of his grace, and haters of purity, he hath ſaid and ſworn that unbelievers ſhall not enter into his reſt, and hath peremp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torily decreed, without hope of repeal, or mitigation of the cenſure, that <hi>If ye live after the fleſh ye ſhall dye.</hi> It's not <hi>fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis operantis,</hi> but <hi>operis;</hi> for they would live after the fleſh, and not dye; they would live like Devils, and dye like Saints; the life of <hi>Balaam,</hi> but the death of the righteous. But he that ſins volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarily, muſt ſuffer involuntarily, there is a connexion of theſe <hi>ab ordine juſtitiae divinae, He that ſoweth to the fleſh, ſhall of the fleſh reape corruption.</hi> Let not man then ſeparate, what God hath joyned; and though he aſſay it, he ſhall never be able to do it. If they will live after the fleſh, they ſhall dye.</p>
            <p>But as St. <hi>Gregory</hi> upon the Parable of the rich man, <hi>Recordatione magis eget ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus iſte quam expoſitione;</hi> ſo I may ſay of
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:170192:22"/>this: therefore we will draw hence ſome Corollaries, which may be for our Spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al direction.</p>
            <p>Firſt then, will ſin couſen us thus?<note place="margin">The Uſe for Informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> who would have ſuſpected that ſuch begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings that promiſed ſuch delight, would have ended thus? that ſo glorious a Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhine morning would have cloſed with ſuch gloomy blaſts, with ſuch thunder, and lightning, ſtormes, and tempeſts? then let no child of God envy the wicked their delight in ſin, not grudge at his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licious fare, Silkes, and Sattins. Much good may do <hi>Nabal</hi> with his good chear, and <hi>Haman</hi> with his preferment. I en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy not the whole world to <hi>Alexander</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſuch hard terms; there is poyſon in their delicates, and clothes are fafcinated, their advancement prefers them to the gibbet, their very life is but a continual death; and how bitter ſhall be the death of theſe men! Rather let me have <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cobs</hi> pillow, and Canopy, ſo I may have his dream; let me have <hi>John Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts</hi> hair-cloth, ſo I may have his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience; No, I admire thoſe worthies of old, that would chooſe to do or ſuffer any thing rather then ſplit themſelves upon theſe rocks. Oh happy confeſſors, and
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:170192:23"/>thrice bleſſed Martyrs, that paſſed tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row fire and water, and refuſed no tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, no death, that they might be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered from the ſecond death. Let me paſſe under <hi>Eſayes</hi> ſaw, and endure <hi>Jere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies</hi> ſhowres of ſtormes; let me not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe <hi>Zacharies</hi> ſword, nor the Lyons den with <hi>Daniel;</hi> let me be beheaded with St. <hi>Paul,</hi> or crucified with <hi>Andrew,</hi> and <hi>Peter;</hi> let me be flayed with <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholomew,</hi> or my braines daſht out with St. <hi>James;</hi> let me be put into a veſſel of ſcalding liquor with St. <hi>John,</hi> or broyled on the Gridiron with <hi>Laurence;</hi> let me ſuffer abſtinence, affliction, perſecution, exile, impriſonment with thoſe holy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of old, <hi>Chryſoſtome, Athanaſius, Ambroſe, Hierom;</hi> let me be given to the wilde beaſts with <hi>Polycarpus,</hi> and <hi>Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natius;</hi> yea, if it were poſſible, let all theſe meet, and the tormentots prompted by the Devil himſelf, ſee if they can in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent any torment more exquiſite; let me ſuffer in this world what humane nature is capable of, rather then be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken by God, and dye ever. Oh bleſſed Chriſtians, that would offer your ſelves rather to your perſecutors in the dayes of <hi>Tertullian, Ego ſum Chriſtianus, Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianus
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:170192:23"/>et ego!</hi> I ſhall ever ſubſcribe to that of holy St. <hi>Aug. Domine hic ure, hic ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca, ut in aeternum parcas;</hi> and again, <hi>Do de me poenas, ut ille parcat,</hi> I had rather ſuffer Gods chaſtiſement then his puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>And I would to God this might be an advertiſement to us all, how we live after the fleſh, though it be pleaſing, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable for a while, yet the event ſhould deter wiſe men. St. <hi>Gregories</hi> memento, to keep him from walking after the fleſh, was this, <hi>Wo to them that are at eaſe in Sion;</hi> St. <hi>Hierom's,</hi> that laſt trump, <hi>Surgite mortui;</hi> St. <hi>Auguſtines,</hi> Not in ſurfeiting and drunkenneſſe; and this may be the Chriſtians, <hi>Moriemini.</hi> And why will ye dye? God delights not in your deſtruction. He hath given you this Memento, that you might not walk after the fleſh. Needs muſt you feel this, if you will not now fear it. Remember this you riotous eaters of fleſh, you that follow wine and ſtrong drink, till you are inflamed; you that inflame your ſoules with luſt, and drown your bodies with a dropſie, that forget God, and the operation of his hands, the Church and the afflictions thereof,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:170192:24"/>your ſelves, and your latter end.</p>
            <p>But now the queſtion is, what it is to be a drunkard? and it muſt be a fair print that the drunkard can read, and with <hi>Anaxagoras,</hi> they will put us to prove, that the ſnow is white. Surely he is a drunkard and glutton, and ſo lives after the fleſh, that eats and drinks inordinate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, immoderately, unſeaſonably. Inor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinately, that directs not theſe to Gods glory, ſo that he is unfit to pray, read, hear on Gods day, or do the works of his calling on other dayes. Let them think of this that are ſo good forenoones men, but ſo bad afternoons. Or immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derately, which immoderation is to be eſtimated according to divers particulars; not alone when it is more then the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach can bear, but when it is more then their eſtate, calling, buſineſſe, or Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion will allow. Or unſeaſonably, and when that is, nature it ſelf (as a Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Prelate of our own hath obſerved) will direct us. When any of theſe four paſſions are predominant, we refuſe ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtenance, anger, fear, grief, deſire. 1. For anger, you ſee <hi>Ahab</hi> refuſed his meat when he was vexed, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 21.4. When our ſtomacks are big with indignation
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:170192:24"/>againſt our ſelves for ſin, it is unſeaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to pamper the fleſh. 2. In fear, ſo <hi>Paul,</hi> and his companions in the ſhip, cannot eat, <hi>Act.</hi> 27. So if we have juſt cauſe of fear in regard of publick cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, let wiſe men judge, <hi>Iſ.</hi> 22.12. If there be fear of loſing the ſoul much more: in the Plague <hi>David,</hi> in War <hi>Jehoſaphat,</hi> in Famine <hi>Joel.</hi> If deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction be impendent, <hi>Heſter,</hi> and the <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nevites</hi> will faſt; and whether it be not ſeaſonable for us to faſt now, let wiſe men judge. 3. In grief, faſting and mourning are joyned together, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 102.4. <hi>My heart is ſmitten and withered like graſſe, ſo that I forget to eat my bread.</hi> So <hi>David,</hi> 2 Sam. 12.15. Much more when we have cauſe to grieve for the abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of our Land, the deſolations of our Neighbour-Countrey, the jeopardy of our own ſoules, and lives, the loſſe of God. 4. In deſire, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 14.24. So <hi>Eſau</hi> in hunting; in regard of better per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of ſome duty, or to obtain ſome ſpecial favour, it will feather our prayers, and put life into them. In a word, when God by his Judgments, or his Subſtitutes by their Edicts call us to faſting, they that eat and drink but
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:170192:25"/>moderately, <hi>live after the fleſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nay, I will go one ſtep further: I ſee no reaſon, but that the looking upon Wine with a luſtful eye, ſhould be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted drunkenneſſe, as well as hatred, and envy, murther; covetouſneſſe, theft; or a wanton luſtful eye, adultery; and if this be to live after the fleſh, how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny embarked in that dangerous Voyage of eternal death! Many like <hi>Dionyſius</hi> lying at a ſiege, would be ſick if they might not ſurfeit, and be drunk now and then. How doth our Land abound with ſuch monſtrous hell-hounds! now ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, and ſcoffing; anon railing, and blaſpheming, diſcloſing ſecrets of State, or Family. Will you have the portrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of it? Like <hi>Circe</hi> it turns men in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all ſhapes. Go into Bedlam, where ſome rave, ſome ſing, ſome whoop, and hollow, ſome cry; or, if you will, view ſome filthy puddle, where ſwine tumble, and wallow themſelves, toads and frogs lie croaking; or, if you will, launch out into the deep, and view the Sea-Monſters. An hoſpital hath not ſo many Lazars, nor a dung-hill ſo many ill ſents, as you ſhall ſee, and ſmell in their meetings. Nay, ſuppoſe all theſe together, its not
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:170192:25"/>a ſufficient expreſſion, you would think devils were come down in the likeneſſe of men, and entred into the ſwine, that drives them headlong into the Sea of Gods wrath. Oh this is a dainty life, thinks the Jovial companion; but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member what followes, Thou muſt dye, and come to Judgment. Hear thy doom written in letters of blood; <hi>Wo to drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kards,</hi> ſaith <hi>Eſay. Wo,</hi> ſaith <hi>Habakkuk: Wo,</hi> ſaith <hi>Solomon; Howl,</hi> ſaith <hi>Joel: Weep,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>James; Ye ſhall dye,</hi> ſaith our Apoſtle; ſcarce a Prophet, or an Apoſtle, but hath thrown a ſtone at him. Look ere long to have a head full of wind, legs ſwollen with water, cheeks blown with ayr, a face red with fire, ever bluſhing, though paſt grace; eyes run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, though not a tear of remorſe; trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling in the joynts, though no fear of Gods Judgments.</p>
            <p>Needs muſt he dye, for this drawes the heart from God, and makes a man break all Gods Commandments, makes his belly his God, blaſphemes his Name, profanes his day, deſpiſeth dominion, and dignity. I have often with indignation ſeen his Majeſties portraiture hang'd up for a ſign, and that ſacred name of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:170192:26"/>uſed in an health, when the frothy mouth, and ſtammering tongue can ſcarcely ſpeak a diſtinct word; it kills more then the ſword, fills more full of prodigious, and Sodomitical luſts, robs God, and Church, poor, family, a mans ſelf; he is a railer, a reviler, a ſlanderer, he hardens his heart againſt God, believes nothing, lives licentiouſly, and the more likely to dye, there is ſo little hope of amendment; he deſpiſeth the Magiſtrate that doth correct him; and for the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter that reproves him, he is the drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kards ſong. How can he repent, that cannot confeſſe? and how can he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, that forgets when he is ſober what he did when he was drunk? If he be of a more melting diſpoſition, it is his liquor that doth facilitate his teares: but he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turnes like the dog to his vomit, ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, and fearleſſe.</p>
            <p>Remember this ye furious hot-ſpurres,<note place="margin">For Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation.</note> if anger command, you'l kill and ſlay; hence ſo much blood. You ſhall dye hereafter, and it's pity you ſhould live here.</p>
            <p>Oh remember this ye debauched ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, foul-mouthed hell-hounds, that fall upon the ſacred body of Chriſt, and tear
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:170192:26"/>him in pieces, ſwear him all over from head to foot, that pull his precious bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy from his ſoul, his blood from his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, that rake in his wounds, and crucifie him afreſh. The curſe ſhall ere long enter into your houſes, and hearts, and never leave you till it bring you to ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine.</p>
            <p>Remember this, ye ambitious <hi>Nimrods,</hi> aſpiring <hi>Hamans,</hi> that to attain your ends, ſwear, forſwear, falter, &amp;c. and climb up this craggy rock, though with never ſo much difficulty, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Conſider this, ye inſatiable ſtallions, that neigh after your neighbours Wives, and glory in your ſhame; you that are perfidious to God and man, forgetting your Marriage-vow, as if your luſt were aſleep, rouze it up, and foment it with laſcivious pictures, ſcurrilous talk, filthy Poems, pictures, Stage-playes, the ſemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naries of filthineſſe; you that <hi>are wiſe to do evil,</hi> and invent prodigious wayes to ſatisfie your luſts. Strange puniſhments ſhall be for ſuch workers of iniquity. Remember <hi>Abſalom</hi> that defiled his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Concubines. Heaven would not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive ſuch a miſcreant, nor the earth bear him, he was hang'd betwixt both. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:170192:27"/>
               <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah,</hi> that burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in unnatural luſts; God ſent fire from heaven to conſume them. But if they eſcape that, a worſe is preparing, it will be at the laſt bitter as wormwood, ſharper then a two-edged ſword.</p>
            <p>Remember this ye haughty perſons that ſpeak ſwelling words of vanity, that wear Lord-ſhips on your backs, that ſpend ſo much time in trimming up that houſe of clay; you men that are ſo effeminate, and women that are grown Monſters, wearing apparel againſt ſhamefaſtneſſe, utility, and decency; you in whom nor Magiſtrate, nor Miniſter can work any reformation, but make idols of your ſelves; take heed God ſend not a rent inſtead of a girdle; and baldneſſe inſtead of your borrowed, powdered, brayded hair. Take heed God do not ſend an enemy to pull off your ridiculous appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel, and diſcover your ſhame to your reproach; but if you eſcape here, you ſhall be ſure to ſmart for it hereafter.</p>
            <p>Remember this ye rich men, you that go clothed in purple and ſcarlet, and fare deliciouſly every day. It's impoſſible for thoſe that <hi>live after the fleſh</hi> to enter into heaven; its very difficult for a rich
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:170192:27"/>man not to live after the fleſh. You may not do with your own what you will, not be proud of your own cloathes, nor play the gluttons with your own food, nor be drunk with your own wine, nor laſcivious with your own wives. Ere long God will poſe yon with theſe two Quaeries; How you came by your wealth; and I will not bid you remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member how much you have hoarded up by ſacriledge, by oppreſſion and couſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age: the ſecond, How you have im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed it, in good chear, in brave appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel, ſo much for the ſatisfying of my vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luptuous pleaſure; ſcarce any for the glory of God in heaven, and poor <hi>Laza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi> on earth. Your account will be wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, you ſtand in ſlippery places; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore by how much wealth encreaſeth, by ſo much had you need to be more watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful.</p>
            <p>Oh <hi>remember this, all ye that forget God, leſt he teare you in pieces when there is none to deliver. Let no man deceive you with vain words; for theſe things ſake the wrath of God comes upon the childaen of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience;</hi> but if nothing will reclaim you, if you will not fear it, you muſt feel it. Go on then thou debauched
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:170192:28"/>ſinner, let looſe the reines to all licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiouſneſſe, pleaſe the fleſh in all ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuality, eat, drink, and be merry; ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count our words as wind, and death, and torment, as ſome Poetical fiction; cloath thy ſelf in purple, and ſcarlet, and fare deliciouſly every day; let the poor dye for want of thy ſuperfluities, prefer thy dogs before poor <hi>Lazarus,</hi> live like an Epicure, like a beaſt, like a devil; but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that deſtruction will overtake thee as a whirlwind; unſatisfied hell will ere long ſend pale death, as an inexora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Sergeant to arreſt thee, and thou ſhalt be caſt into priſon, and not come thence till thou haſt paid the uttermoſt farthing. Time will come, when having irrecoverably loſt the bleſſing with <hi>Eſau,</hi> thou wilt howl; and ſay; <hi>Bleſſe me, even me alſo;</hi> but there ſhall be no place for repentance. As a man that ſeeth a coſtly feaſt, when he himſelf is pined; thou ſhalt ſee <hi>Abraham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> ſet down at Gods Table, then ſhalt thou think, There is ſuch a one whom I once ſcorned, now <hi>he is comforted, I am tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented:</hi> Ah wretch that I am, I was invited as well as he; Alas! how much precious time have I now miſ-ſpent,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:170192:28"/>wherein I might have gained much to mine own ſoul? how many admonitions have I contemned? and now it's irreco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verably come upon me. How oſt hath Chriſt opened his wounds to heal me? ſtretched out his arms to receive me? intreated me not to grieve his Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, nor to crucifie him afreſh? With what earneſt ſollicitations hath he wooed me to be reconciled, but I would not? Oh what doth it profit me now that I have been cloathed in purple and ſcarlet! &amp;c. How much better had it been for me to have been the very off<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcouring of the world, <hi>a worm and no man?</hi> yea, better for me that I had never been, or might yet at the laſt ceaſe to be; but all this is now juſtly come upon me, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I would not hear my Saviour, and his meſſengers, nor pity mine own ſoul; but while I was ſeeking my veniſon, have loſt my bleſſing.</p>
            <p>But if all this will not avail, to dehort men from living after the fleſh, give me leave to turn my ſpeech to you Reverend Sages, whom under his Majeſty, God hath placed at our ſtern. Let it be your care to revive thoſe gaſping Lawes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted againſt ſwearing, and ſurfeiting,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:170192:29"/>and drunkenneſſe, &amp;c. not onely for the puniſhing, but for the preventing of this latter: for this purpoſe remember your oaths; do not play with the Evangeliſts, as it is the fault of too many; elſe you through your neglect, may bring ruine to the Land, and the blood of theſe men upon your heads. <hi>Impunitas auſum parit, auſus exceſſum;</hi> ſo the ſin will be ulti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mately terminated in you: and princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally let your lives be exemplary, reform your families; let not your Cellars be turned into Ale-houſes, nor your houſes ſhops for the devil. Tophet is enlarged for ſuch that <hi>live after the fleſh,</hi> and by their example draw others.</p>
            <p>And you that have the Eccleſiaſtical power, Oh improve it to Gods glory, and for his ſake quicken diſcipline againſt theſe walkers after the fleſh; If they will needs die, pull them by violence out of the fire. Let not the ſword ruſt in the ſheath, or if you do draw it, think it not enough to flouriſh it; and if you will ſtrike, lay on upon theſe walkers after the fleſh. Oh give not Church-Wardens cauſe to complain, that they ſtill preſent, but can ſee no reformation; nor the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquent to boaſt that they can eſcape
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:170192:29"/>with a ten groats ſee; nor the ſoules of theſe men to complain hereafter, that if the fleſh had been puniſhed, the ſpirit had been ſaved in the day of Chriſt. Let Miniſters preach, and people pray, and Magiſtrates puniſh, and delinquents re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form, and all mourn, leſt our patient God, for our tranſcendent abominations cauſe our Land to ſpue out her Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants.</p>
            <p>But if none of theſe will perſwade, then let thoſe that live after the fleſh, know, that their deſtruction is from themſelves: God hath gathered the ſtones out of the vineyard by his preventing grace, fenced thee about, given thee the ſweet influence of his grace, <hi>the former, and latter rain;</hi> and now judge thou who art a party, whether there hath any thing been want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on Gods part, to make thee happy; but thou wilt needs dye, not becauſe thou loveſt death, but ſin which is the cauſe of it.</p>
            <p>And let us all remember, that our worſt enemy is within us. <hi>Bern. Ipſi geſtamus laqueum, nobiſcum circumferimus ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micum;</hi> We carry a ſnare about with us, our own enemy is within us. We are beaten like <hi>Judah,</hi> with our own ſtaffe,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:170192:30"/>and manacled with our own bracelets; yea, with <hi>Saul</hi> we ſlay our ſelves with our own ſword. It's a Serpent in our own boſome that ſtings us, <hi>Inimici ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minis ſunt ejus domeſtici,</hi> A mans foes are thoſe of his own houſe. He that dips with us in the diſh is it that betrayes us. Blame not Satan, or his inſtruments, theſe could not kill us, but that this Traytour opens the doors, their temptations elſe would fall like a ſpark of fire in the Sea, much leſſe let us murmur againſt God; though he be the inflicting cauſe, yet ſin is the meritorious.</p>
            <p>Take heed of this enemy ſo much the rather, for it's a potent and politick ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, being an old man that receives in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence from the Devil; it's worſe then the Devil, who hath ſome natural goodneſſe, wiſdome, and power, which in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves are good, though by him abuſed. But in the fleſh dwells no good thing, it fills the whole man full of impiety; as the mind with wicked thoughts, making it like a dark filthy Dungeon, full of Snakes and Adders, deſtitute of heavenly light and heat; the imaginations of it onely evil continually; and if the beſt part be ſo, what is the worſt? It's a ſtore-houſe,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:170192:30"/>or a common ſewer of abominations, fills the eye full of Adultery, the counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of wrath, makes the throat an open ſepulchre, the tongue a world of wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: if a world in that little member; how many worlds in this little world of ours? fills the hand with extortion, makes the feet ſwift to ſhed blood; in a word, all the Devils brats are warmed, conceived, and bred in that wombe: it's an enemy to all Spiritual undertakings; what is wiſdome to the Spirit, is fooliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to the fleſh; what the one willeth, the other nilleth; what the one endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours, the other croſſeth; it breakes all Lawes, both of God and man, and makes unreaſonable Lawes of its own, of ſin and death, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.23.8.2. Of ſinne, therefore diſhonourable to live after them, for it gives unreaſonable com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand. He that obeyeth hath <hi>Chams</hi> curſe, to be a ſervant of ſervants. But the ſervice is dangerous, in that rewarded with ſuch wages; <hi>for the wages of ſin is death;</hi> worſe then for a man to ſerve at the Gallies all day, and be hanged at night. Therefore of all enemies, let us take moſt heed of our ſelves; theſe luſts within us fight agaiſt us, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.11. they hunt for
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:170192:31"/>the precious life; and if we yeeld to them, we dye. He that ſoweth the wind, ſhall reape the whirlwind. <hi>If we ſowe to the fleſh, we ſhall of the fleſh reape corruption; but he that ſoweth to the Spirit, ſhall of the Spirit reape life everlaſting; For if ye live after the fleſh, ye ſhall dye; but if ye by the Spirit mortifie the deeds of the body, ye ſhall live.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But if ye by the Spirit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olation.</note> &amp;c. Now I am fallen on the ſecond Propoſition, the Conſolation. Hitherto I have tyred your patience with a diſcourſe of the works of darkneſſe, and a ſad narration of death, the reward of ſuch works; give me leave now to entertain your ears with a more pleaſing diſcourſe of life, and of the nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row way that leads thither. <hi>If ye by the Spirit, &amp;c.</hi> The fleſh like a potent King domineers in a natural man, and makes him yeeld obedience to it in the luſts thereof; yea, in a regenerate man it remains, though weakned and wounded, like the <hi>Canaanites;</hi> if it cannot dwell in the City, it will lodge in the ſubburbs; though it raign not like a King, it will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel like a Traytor, ſometimes aſſault<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by open violence; ſometimes by ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret ambuſhments, and hidden ſtrata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gems,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:170192:31"/>undermining; ſo that while he dwells in this tabernacle of fleſh, the fleſh will continue in him; his labour ſhall not end, ſo long as his life doth continue: while we live then we ſhall find work enough to keep under this rebel; and to encourage us herein, God hath given us ſuch an help as will effect it, his Spirit; and propounded ſuch a motive, as may ſpur on the dulleſt <hi>Laodicean, Ye ſhall live.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here the Apoſtle doth theſe two things,<note place="margin">Divided.</note>1. <hi>Proponit officium, If ye,</hi> &amp;c. 2. <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittit mercedem.</hi> Firſt the work, then the wages; firſt we muſt do the will of God, then receive the promiſe: firſt God muſt be glorified by us, and then he will glorifie us; the hardeſt that is firſt, and that we muſt look to, to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie; the ſweeteſt comes laſt, and that God will care for, <hi>Ye ſhall live.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the firſt we note theſe particulars;<note place="margin">Subdivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</note>1. <hi>Octjectum, deeds of the body.</hi> 2. <hi>Actio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem circa objectum,</hi> Ye muſt <hi>mortifie the deeds of the body.</hi> 3. <hi>Cauſas hujus actic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis, principalem,</hi> the Spirit; <hi>minus prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipalem,</hi> we.</p>
            <p>Firſt,<note place="margin">The deeds of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy what.</note> for the object about which mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification is converſant, <hi>the deeds of the
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:170192:32"/>body.</hi> Here we muſt explicate both the fountain, and ſtreams. Some underſtand a metonymie in this word <hi>body,</hi> ſo by it underſtand the natural body, becauſe ſin is acted by the body. Others underſtand it metaphorically of that old man, and maſſe of corruption that is in every man, called <hi>the body of ſin,</hi> Rom. 6.6. &amp; 7.24. Col. 2.11. for as the body is a <hi>totum in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrum,</hi> conſiſting of many members, ſo is ſin, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.4. the head of ſin, <hi>vain imaginations;</hi> the heart of ſin, <hi>corrupt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections;</hi> the tongue of ſin, <hi>rotten commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication;</hi> the forehead of ſin, <hi>impudent avouching;</hi> the hands and feet of ſinne, <hi>wicked executions.</hi> Again, as the body hath its dimenſions, ſo hath ſin; it reach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to heaven, and burneth to the loweſt hell; is's of as great a latitude as Gods Commandments, which are exceeding broad. 3. As the body is knit together by joynts, and ligaments, ſo is ſin. If the foot of ſin do but ſtirre, the whole body moves, as we ſee in the ſin of <hi>Adam. He that offends in one, is guilty of all;</hi> he ſins againſt the general equity of the Law, and righteouſneſſe of the Law-giver. As the body compaſſeth us about, ſo doth ſin, it's <hi>peccatum circumſtans;</hi> that for
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:170192:32"/>the firſt, by the <hi>body</hi> we mean the body of ſin.</p>
            <p>Secondly, For <hi>the deeds of the body.</hi> This old man, though old, yet is very ſtirring and operative. When men grow old, their apprehenſion is weak, their memory dull, the ſtrong men bow, the whole man is feeble; but it is not ſo in the body of ſin, the older it is, the more vigorous, and luſty. Nothing in the world ſo fruitful; though theſe are but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, unfruitful works. Of Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, none ſo fruitful as water; ſtinking puddles bring forth moſt troops of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine. Some grounds yield two crops every year; ſome trees bear fruit twice, this all the year; ſome creatures breed every moneth, this every moment; and theſe brats are even conceived and born at once. How many kinds are there of ſins? and how many millions of each kind? <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.21. There is ſome of the progeny, it is <hi>progenies viperarum;</hi> all thoſe irregular thoughts, affections, words and actions that paſſe from a man, come from hence. Now this body hath its activeneſſe from the parents, the father is the devil, a compaſſer; the ſoul the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, in perpetual motion, and agitation.
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:170192:33"/>Now his own will enticeth him to theſe deeds; and he that is wilfully bent upon a thing, who can ſtay him? The Devil continually ſpurs him on, and he muſt needs go whom the Devil drives; he is fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther provoked by the world, by the men of the world, their perſwaſion as <hi>Solomon,</hi> their threats as <hi>Nebuchadnezzar,</hi> their promiſes as <hi>Balaam,</hi> their example as <hi>Jeroboam:</hi> by the things of the world; there is at leaſt a ſeeming luſtre in the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject that doth allure; <hi>Bathſheba's</hi> beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, the rich wedge of gold, and the Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byloniſh garment. When the Veſſel ſailes with the tide, and the ſailes blown with ſuch a gale, it muſt needs go apace. There are deeds of the body which are natural, to eat, drink, ſleep; voluntary, to walk, &amp;c. but theſe are <hi>motus, &amp; opera carnis peccatricis,</hi> theſe are they that muſt be mortified; that is the ſecond thing in the duty.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mortifie]</hi> The body of death muſt be ſlain that we may live:<note place="margin">What it is to mortifie.</note> Thus if we will become wiſe, we muſt firſt be fooles; if rich, and have a Kingdome, poor in ſpirit; if free, put our necks under Chriſts yoke; if ſave our life; firſt loſe it, if have a true being, old men muſt be
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:170192:33"/>born again; if have the life of grace here, and glory hereafter, firſt kill our ſinful ſelves. To <hi>mortifie,</hi> is a Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phor taken from Chirurgeons that uſe to mortifie that part they mean to cut off; ſo we muſt mortifie ſin, that it may not live; or if it live ſuch a life as is left in the limbs when the head is ſtruck off, or as in thoſe that have an Epilepſie,<note place="margin">Rom. 4.19.</note> or as in old <hi>Abrahams</hi> body, which was as good as dead, unfit for generation. The efficacy and power of theſe luſts muſt be ſlain, that they produce not new Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, and ſo bring forth fruit unto death; that is, (as <hi>Cajetan</hi> tells us) <hi>inſur gentes compeſcendo, ne inſurgant domando,</hi> ſo mortifie them that they make no rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion; or if they do make inſurrection, beat them down that they domineer not. So much for the ſecond thing, the act.</p>
            <p>I come now to the cauſes.<note place="margin">The effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient cauſe principal the Spirit.</note> The princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal is the Spirit. By the Spirit here (to omit other acceptations) we under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand either the grace of the Spirit, or the Spirit of grace. If the former, then ſo far forth as it is enlivened, and actuated by the latter. The Spirit dwells in all crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures by a general influence, in Chriſt by hypoſtatical union, in ſome men by creating
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:170192:34"/>in them extraordinary gifts, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; in the elect by effectual operation. And if the eſſence of the Spirit be in us, it is in us, not as an eſſential part, that were to deify man; nor united perſonally unto us, for then ſhould the third perſon be incarnate as well as the ſecond; but dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in Chriſt as the head, in an unſpeaka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble manner diffuſed unto us. Thus the devil dwells in the children of diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, not by communicating his eſſence to them, for then they ſhould be incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate devills, but taking poſſeſſion of them as his vaſſals, blinding their minds, har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dening their hearts, infuſing malice into their wills, leading them captive, till at the laſt he bring them to the pit of deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. But hath man the command of the Spirit? But the Spirit and Gods Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances are not ſeparated, unleſſe for our fault. But is the Spirit our inſtrument? No, but we the Spirits; for God infu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth into us this ſupernatural principle, whereby we are inabled to work, and then quickeneth it up by moral perſwaſion. But how doth the Spirit mortifie? It's that light that doth detect thoſe deeds of the body: it's contrary to them, and ſtirs up hatred againſt them: it's the Spirit of
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:170192:34"/>grace which makes us pray againſt them; it's our remembrance that brings to our mind the Scripture, that declares the odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe and danger of them; it's the mighty power of God, that cruſheth theſe brats in pieces: it's that which doth co-operate with the Word, and prayer, and tears, and affliction, and faſting, whereby the fleſh is beaten down. That the Spirit worketh, we evidently feel, but how, we cannot certainly define: for if the operation of the wind, the framing of the body in the womb be ſo ſtrange, much more that of the Spirit.</p>
            <p>The leſſe-principal cauſe, We.<note place="margin">The leſſe-principal, We.</note> The Spirit quickens us being dead, and being quickened we muſt act by the Spirit. In the receiving the firſt grace man is a meer paſſive, <hi>habet ſe ut materia:</hi> in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond partly active, partly paſſive; active, we muſt mortify; paſſive, for it muſt be by the Spirit; and as St. <hi>Aug. Gratia non cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit, non reſipiſcit, non ſperat, non obtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perat Deo, ſed homo per gratiam;</hi> Grace be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves not, repents not, hopes not, obeys not God, but man by grace. So we ſay, <hi>Spiritus non mortificat, ſed homo per Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritum;</hi> The Spirit mortifies not, but man by the Spirit; that we might not be proud
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:170192:35"/>or ſelf confident, not we, but the Spirit; that we might not be ſlothful, or negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent, we muſt do it by the Spirit; that we might avoid all ſtraines of Popery and Pelagianiſm, it is the Spirit which quickens us at the firſt, and doth continually ſend us freſh ſupplies againſt the fleſh; that we might not be taken with the idle fancies or doting dreames and crotchets of the Familiſts, we muſt mortifie by the Spirit. As we cannot mortifie without the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, ſo the Spirit will not without us.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ye ſhall live.</hi> Having now done with the duty,<note place="margin">What life here meant.</note> we come to the reward, and what is better then life? God is pleaſed to be ſtiled a living God. This is that which every eye looks at, every heart breaths after, in which the vaſteſt deſire is ſatisfied, beyond which the mind knowes nothing, nor the will deſires any thing that might make it happy.</p>
            <p>By life here we do not underſtand the uncreated life of God, but the created life of man, which is twofold: corporal, the union of the ſoul with the body; ſpiritual, the union of God with the ſoul. Indeed there is a natural life of the ſoul, like that of Angels, in which ſenſe damned ſpirits
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:170192:35"/>may be ſaid to live; this was the eternity the Philoſophers knew of. So <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">3. de an. c. 5.</note> this being concreated with the ſoul can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be taken away, but by annihilating of it. The ſoul conſidered ſpiritually may be dead while it thus lives, if it be ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated from God in regard of holineſſe and happineſſe.</p>
            <p>We will briefly ſee what this includes, <hi>Ye ſhall live,</hi> that is, ye ſhall not dye; and how happy would the damned ſpirits think themſelves, if they might not dye, though they might not live, that indeed they might not be at all rather then ſo mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable!</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ye ſhall live,</hi> That is, a happy life here,<note place="margin">Natural.</note> a natural life full of joy and comfort. Godlineſſe, which includes mortification, hath the promiſe of this life; our cloathes ſhall warm us, our food nonriſh us. Though men out of Covenant have a right to theſe, if they come by them lawfully, yet a ſanctified uſe they have not, but by vertue of the Covenant, as our cloaths receive heat from us, and then warm us.</p>
            <p>You ſhall live when you die, and death ſhall be as the port, after all the toſſings
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:170192:36"/>and tumults of this life, the Phyſician that cures all diſeaſes, the point that puts a period to all our labours; it's the reward of piety, at the leaſt an entrance into that reward, and the birth-day of eternity, the end of our ſorrow, the way to our Countrey, the beginning of glory, a general antidote for all aggrievances. God is their God while they live in the grave, and hath engaged his Word to reſtore them at the laſt day.<note place="margin">Joh. 11.</note> 
               <hi>He that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieveth in me ſhall live, though he dye; and he that liveth, and believeth in me, ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver dye. Vitam non eripit, ſed intermittit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the ſpiritual life of a Chriſtian is that which is moſt excellent,<note place="margin">Spiritual, of grace.</note> and that flowes from the union of God with the ſoul, diſtinguiſhed into degrees: the firſt from converſion to the time of death, when God by his Spirit breathes on the dead lump of ſin and clay, and makes it a glorious creature after his own Image, <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.24. This is called <hi>the life of God,</hi> Eph. 4.18. becauſe it comes from God as the fountain, inſomuch that he doth live in them; and if God be at all the life and ſoul of the world, (as the <hi>Platoniſts</hi> ſay) it is meant of Chriſtians principally. The entrance into this life
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:170192:36"/>is through the gate of regeneration, this parallells that <hi>vitam plantae,</hi> and that firſt degree of natural life in the womb. <hi>Ye ſhall live;</hi> That is, the life of grace.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>Ye ſhall live,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Of glory.</note> the life of glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in the firſt degree, from the death of the body to the reſurrection of it; When the body ſleepeth in the grave ſweetned by Chriſts burial, the ſoul ſhall be carried by the miniſtery of Angels into <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hams</hi> boſome, <hi>Luk.</hi> 16.22. Though there be not in this eſtate a plenary conſumma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of happineſſe, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.8. <hi>Apcc.</hi> 6.9. yet the Spirit returnes to God, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 12.7. to Chriſt, <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.23. it reſts from labour, is in comfort, ſo it was ſaid of <hi>Lazarus, Luk.</hi> 16.25. to Paradiſe, ſo to the thief, <hi>Matth.</hi> 24.32. <hi>Luk.</hi> 23.43. Without doubt with great ſolemnity, and joy do the holy Saints and Angels receive the ſoul into heaven; into this degree we enter by the gate of death, and it parallels the life of an animal, and the ſecond degree of natural life in men, from the birth till they come to the uſe of reaſon.</p>
            <p>In the ſecond degree, you ſhall live the life of glory in regard of the conſummati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of it, from the day of the reſurrection to all eternity, enjoying the full viſion,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:170192:37"/>and fruition of God: where you ſhall ſee God ſitting on his throne in inacceſſible light, and Jeſus Chriſt ſitting on his right hand with an innumerable company of Saints and Angels attending on him, all ſhining as the Sun in the Firmament, where all ſorrow ceaſeth for ever, and a conflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of all deſirable happineſſe.</p>
            <p>It may be ſome will enquire what our converſation ſhall be there; for your meat and drinke, there is Angels food, a tree of life; for your apparel, long white robes of righteouſneſſe; for your muſicke, a quire of Angels; riches and glory are in this place, the houſe is made of gold, and the pave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of precious ſtones. As for honour, every man ſhall be a king, and reigne in bliſſe; and for delight, at his right hand there are pleaſures for evermore; for knowledge, we ſhall ſee face to face; and for liberty, the body ſhall be made ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual; <hi>Siquidem ubi volet ſpiritus, ibi erit corpus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In a word, they ſhall enjoy God, in whom is eminently contained all perſecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and glory. If a little earthly glory a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maze, as it did <hi>Herod,</hi> what will that above do? If there be ſuch glory in Gods foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoole, what is there in his throne? <hi>Si
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:170192:37"/>tanta nobis tribuis in carcere, quid dabis in patria? Si tanta tribuis inimicis, quid ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis?</hi> If, O Lord, thou giveſt us ſo much in the land of our pilgrimage, what wilt thou give us in our own countrey? if ſo much to thine enemies, what wilt thou give to thy friends? The Hebrews report, how truely I know not, that when <hi>Joſeph</hi> had gathered much corne in <hi>Aegypt,</hi> he threw the chaffe into the river <hi>Nilus,</hi> that ſo float<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the neighbour-Cities, and Nations, they might know what abundance was laid up, not for themſelves alone, but for their neighbours alſo: ſo God to make us know what glory is in heaven, hath thrown ſome huskes to us here, that ſo taſting the ſweetneſſe of theſe things we might aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpire to his bounty above. And ſurely, if the outward pavement of the baſe Court doth ſo glitter with ſtars, what is there within? Though we cannot meaſure the content of the ſoule by the outſide of the houſe, no more then you can meaſure the comforts of a Chriſtian by the gay outſide of a Church.</p>
            <p>If I ſhould undertake a full relation of this, my muddy expreſſions would cloud it from you more then declare it; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I leave it to your apprehenſion, as a
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:170192:38"/>thing beyond expreſſion, yea, beyond con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit, while we dwell in theſe houſes of clay. If <hi>Moſes</hi> his face did ſhine with converſing with God; if the Diſciples were ſo raviſhed in the transfiguratiou; if S. <hi>Paul</hi> that ſaw not all, ſaw more then he could utter; and if the ſoules of Gods people are filled with unſpeakable joy, and ſatisfied as with marrow, and fatneſſe, that ſee, and enjoy God but in part here obſcurely; there is ſomthing tranſcendent in the perfect viſion and fruition of God. Theſe little baites ſerve to ſtay our ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macks till we come to that glorious re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſt.<note place="margin">Aug. l. <hi>4.</hi> de. civil. D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Aug. Quod Deus praepara vit diligen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus, fide non accipitur, ſpe non attingitur, charitate non comprehenditur, acquiri poteſt, aeſtimari non poteſt:</hi> Faith cannot compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend, hope cannot reach, charity cannot fathome, what God hath prepared for thoſe that love him; obtained it may be, but never to its worth valued, and eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. And elſewhere, <hi>Facilius poſſumus dicere quid ibi non ſit, quam quid ſit: non eſt ibi mors, non eſt luctus, &amp;c.</hi> We can more eaſily ſay what there is not there, then what there is: there is no death, no mourning, &amp;c. Let us labour to walke in the way, then we ſhall experimentally
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:170192:38"/>feel it, and then even laugh at our ſcanty expreſſions when the ſoule being filled with admiration ſhall cry out, <hi>How full of glory art thou O Lord,</hi> and this heavenly Paradiſe of thine! I have heard of thee by thy Prophets, and Apoſtles, but the one halfe hath not been reſolved. Oh bleſſed is the man that heareth thy wiſdome, ſeeth, and enjoyeth thy glory.</p>
            <p>But by the way note here, that life is referred to mortification, not as the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per cauſe. He that lives after the fleſh, ſhall dye, by his own merit; but he that lives after the Spirit, ſhall live by Gods mercy, and the merit of Chriſt; for he that lives after the fleſh, acts by a princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of his own; but he that by the Spirit, from an hgher principle, and that imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly. So, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6. <hi>ult.</hi> the Apoſtle ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth death is an effect of ſin, life a conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent of righteouſneſſe in a different manner: death followeth ſin as a juſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of it, as a debt, <hi>The wages of ſin is death;</hi> but righteouſneſſe produceth life, as a conſequent, not of debt, but of grace. <hi>The gift of God is eternal life through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord;</hi> that as he attributes no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to man in the latter, ſo he wholly cleareth God in the former.</p>
            <pb n="70" facs="tcp:170192:39"/>
            <p>But ever remember what the good Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſaith, <hi>Acquiri poteſt, aeſtimari non po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt:</hi> It may be gotten, but cannot be va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lued. It's poſſible for to attaine it, but it will coſt thee deare; thou muſt enter in through many tribulations; <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nicus qui introivit ſine peccato, non exivit ſine flagel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo,</hi> thou muſt deny the world, and be cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied to that, hate father, mother, life, thine own life; but that is not all, thou muſt mortifie the deeds of the body. Now if any deſire to enter into life, I muſt firſt aske him, whether he can drinke of this cup, and be baptized with this Baptiſme? he muſt mortifie this body, this old man; corruption is ſtrong, for it's a man; poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique, for an old man; a man that is natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralized in us, and pleads preſcription.</p>
            <p>The old man with all his members, pull out the right eye, cut off the right hand, teare, and re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t the heart aſunder, crowne the head with thornes, pierce the hands &amp; feet with nailes, and the ſide with a ſpeare, the face muſt be ſpit upon, buffetted.</p>
            <p>The body, and all the deeds of it. <hi>Put off the old man with his deeds,</hi> Col. 3. and here mortifie the deeds of the body, and the deeds of the body are manifeſt. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver tell me of a good heart, if the actions
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:170192:39"/>are naught, as the underſtanding blind, the will obſtinate, the affections diſordered, the life diſſolute, this man is out of the way to life. What! a good Chriſtian, and a drunkard, a ſwearer, a ſcoffer at the good wayes of God? It's impoſſible. Is the tree good that is fruitleſſe? Do you call that a good ground, that bears no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but briars, and brambles? The body with the deeds, all the deeds muſt be mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified. Away then with that ſweet mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel under the tongue; if thou willingly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertaine but one ſin conſtantly, ſuppoſe contemplative adultery, thou art an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortified man.</p>
            <p>Againe, theſe muſt be mortified, not trifle, or deale more gently with them, pull up theſe weeds by the very roots; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it muſt be with paine, and ſhame, and conſtant; for it is an act of the whole life, preſcribed here to the Romans, ſo to the Coloſſians. It may be their acquaintance will reproach thee, and thy beſt friends forſake thee.</p>
            <p>And all this we muſt do in our per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, not buy it out, or do it by our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puties; we, by the Spirit, and there is no other way but this to life.</p>
            <p>Nor do I make the way ſtraiter, or the
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:170192:40"/>gate narrower, then Chriſt, and his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles have done. Nor do I here diſhearten any, but require them ſedulouſly to ſet about the worke; better know it now then hereafter when it is too late. <hi>Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life is the gift of God,</hi> that the Scripture ſhews, and reaſon manifeſts, that it is in the power of the donor to preſcribe what conditions he will to the receiver; but the wretchedneſſe of the world is ſuch, they deſire the bleſſing without the condition; like <hi>Ruths</hi> kinſman, that would have the land without the woman; like that man in the Goſpel, would have eternal life, but the condition is too ſtrict, therefore go a way ſorrowful. Thus, how contrary are we to our ſelves, how unreaſonable to God? In the former we would do the work, but not have wages, live after the fleſh, but not die; and in the latter we will not do the labour, yet hope for the reward, as <hi>Balaam</hi> will follow the wages of iniquity, yet die the death of the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous. But if we do the one, the other will follow. And ſurely had we made our own termes, how could we in modeſty have made them more eaſie? God could do no leſſe then demonſtrate his purity, love of vertue, hatred of ſin. God delights not
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:170192:40"/>to make us ſad without cauſe. Certainly he cannot require any thing leſſe then mortification without the impeachment of his honour, therefore we cannot per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form leſſe without the endangering of our happineſſe.</p>
            <p>So then I muſt tell our debauched ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</hi> For Repr.</note> that ſuffer all manner of abominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to raign, not to be named among Chriſtians, and are ſo far from crucifying them, that they harbour, and keep them cloſe, extenuate, defend them, are careful to ſatisfy their luſts, and blow them up to a greater flame, that will be ready to give the ſtab to thoſe that croſſe and contradict them in their waies; there is a thing in Religion called Mortifying the deeds of the body, which they were never acquainted withal, without which there is no life.</p>
            <p>I muſt tell our plauſible Atheiſts, that are enemies to the power of godlineſſe, that have no grace and vertue but what was born and bred with them; it is not their plauſible carriage will do it; there is a mortifying, crucifying, watching, faſting, ſtriving, denying thy ſelf, or no entrance into life.</p>
            <p>I muſt tell our careleſſe procraſtinators
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:170192:41"/>of repentance. It's not enough to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like ſin, and ſo let it alone in time to dye it ſelf, and therefore they will not task themſelves with ſuch an unpleaſing tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but you muſt mortifie it. The fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy adulterer reſolves, when he hath no more marrow in his bones, nor vigour in his body, to leave his adultery; the drunkard his company when his patrimony is ſpent; the oppreſſour his extortion, when his co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetouſneſſe is ſatiated. Sinne, though it be left in regard of the outward act, yet in this caſe it is not mortified, but retired to the inner cloſet of the ſoul, wanting op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity to axpreſſe it ſelf outwardly; and in this caſe it is damnable; for luſting is adultery, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.28. hatred is murther, 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.15. and he that will inhabit heaven, muſt have both <hi>clean hands and a pure heart,</hi> Pſ. 24.4. and the tree is not dead, though it want leaves and fruit; and this conqueſt (if there be any) is to be attributed to the weakneſſe of nature rather then the ſtrength of grace; or elſe here is a <hi>Metempſychoſis</hi> of ſinne; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as a ſinne of youth prevailed before, now a ſin of age domineereth. Thus a man oft-times changeth his favourites. No man in every eſtate, and condition is prone to act the ſame ſins.
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:170192:41"/>
            </p>
            <p>I muſt tell our civil Juſtitiaries, and painted hypocrites; It's not enough to take ſin priſoner, and a little to curbe and reſtrain it, as <hi>Eli</hi> did his ſons; or to cry out, as <hi>Pharaoh</hi> did when he was upon the rack, and ſoon return like the dog to the vomit; we muſt not onely fight, but overcome, if we mean to be crowned; judge, condemne, and mortifie this old man with his deeds.</p>
            <p>I muſt tell our luke-warme <hi>Laodiceans,</hi> that are half perſwaded to be Chriſtians with <hi>Agrippa,</hi> it will not ſerve their turn. If they will almoſt be religious, they ſhall be almoſt ſaved, but altogether damned. To ſpare ſome fat ſins (as <hi>Saul</hi> the cattel) for ſacrifice, to make <hi>ex rapina holocauſtum;</hi> to rob the Church, and build an Hoſpital, or maintain a Free-Schoole; to caſt away ſome ſin, which to them hath neither profit, nor pleaſure in it, and if it were commanded would ſin in omitting it: this is no mortification. It will not avail you to abhorre Idols, ſo long as you commit ſacriledge; that can endure <hi>John Baptiſt,</hi> till he come to touch the apple of your eye; this is but to pair the nayles, or clip the hair of this old man, not to mortifie the body with
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:170192:42"/>his deeds. A Penknife may cut a mans throat, one leake ſink a ſhip, one ſparkle burn an houſe, one ſin ſlay the ſoul.</p>
            <p>I muſt tell thoſe that would be accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted profeſſours, that this word doth not ſufficiently expreſſe the condition of a good Chriſtian; they muſt be practiſers. It is not enough to ſay, The Temple of the Lord; the rich man was a ſon of <hi>Abraham,</hi> yet in hell; to hear a multitude and variety of Sermons; the devil heares more. Though they could hear men of Seraphical ſpirits; the <hi>Capernaites</hi> heard Chriſt, and notwithſtanding this, they were thrown down to hell. You muſt mortify. I cannot but with indignation complain to ſee at leaſt the outward form of Godlineſſe changed, from what it was in the primitive times; and I am perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded ſhould one of our forefathers riſe from the dead, he would as much wonder at the alteration of the faſhion in Religion as apparel. The devotion of the Church of old was to joyn in publique prayer, this is accounted but Idolatrous Superſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by many, and cold devotion by the moſt. Of old it was Religion to keep the body under by faſting, and diſcipline; this practice is not known now of many, prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:170192:42"/>by few: they will loſe their birth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rights, rather then pottage: either they are troubled with wind, or ſome infirmity or other, they cannot faſt; The truth is they are like <hi>Dionyſius</hi> an epicure, who when he lay at a ſiege, and was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to keep a diet, fell ſick becauſe he might not ſurfeit. Of old, charity and good workes were in faſhion, but now he is almoſt accounted a Popeling that will preach for charity, and (God help us) an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy to the State, that exhorteth to peace. I condemn not all, but the religion of too many conſiſts onely in hearing ſuch men; and the height of their practice, to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtain from ſome ſinnes, which are cryed down. I honour the publique preaching of Gods Word in ſeaſon, and out of ſeaſon, and he that oppoſeth it, is an enemy to Chriſt, and his king dome: but if he that preacheth unto others may be a reprobate unleſſe he do beat down his body, and mortifie his ſinne, then he that heareth others much more.</p>
            <p>I muſt tell our curious Correctors of things indifferent, that it is not the eager cenſuring, and condemning they know not what, nor their envying againſt Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, and Ceremonies; and in the mean
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:170192:43"/>time to harbour pride, and paſſion, and uncharitableneſſe; the matter is not what thou canſt ſay, or cenſure in other men, but what thou haſt mortified of thine own.</p>
            <p>Nor will the keeping of outward or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders ſerve the turn; at the beſt if they go no further, they are no better then Scribes and Phariſees, that tithe Mint, and Cummin, and Aniſe, and leave the weighty matters of the Law undone.</p>
            <p>I muſt tell our Solifidans, that boaſt of ſtrange ſpeculations of faith without ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctity: For ought I know, there are a great many Orthodox men in Hell, and while they live in lying, pride, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faneneſſe, their faith without works will not ſave them.</p>
            <p>I muſt tell our refined wits, and great Clerks: It will not avail though they know the abſtruſeſt myſteries that are; yea, all things knowable, as ſome ſay of <hi>Berengarius.</hi> Knowledge without cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity profits nothing: there is neither true piety, nor charity, ſo long as men live after the fleſh, while they continue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolate. I never knew ſuch a way to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, as from bed to board; from hoard to play, &amp;c.</p>
            <pb n="79" facs="tcp:170192:43"/>
            <p>I muſt tell our Popiſh, and Pelagian Doctors, advancers of free-will, that they cannot mortifie themſelves by any power of the fleſh: for corrupt nature agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth well enough with it ſelf; but walk in the Spirit, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.6. not by any Moral or gentle perſwaſion, or by any violent re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint. They that deny grace, or call grace by the name of nature; or ſay, that it is profitable, not neceſſary, or neceſſary for our entrance, not our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance in the wayes of God. Here we ſee, that as by preventing grace we are made Saints, ſo by ſubſequent, and coo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perating grace we are enabled to work like Saints; and it's the Spirit that doth inchoate, continue, conſummate all good in us; whence our Saviour ſaith, <hi>Without me ye can do nothing;</hi> upon which words, St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> gloſſeth thus, <hi>Non dicit, Sine me parum poteſtis fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere, nec dicit Ardui aliquid Sine me non poteſtis facere, vel Difficulter ſine me pote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtis facere, ſed Nihil ſine me poteſtis. Nec dicit, Sine me non poteſtis perfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere, ſed Nihil poteſtis facere ſine me;</hi> He doth not ſay, we can do but little or no great matter, or very difficultly without Chriſt. He doth not ſay, we
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:170192:44"/>can perfect nothing without him, but ſimply do nothing without him.</p>
            <p>I muſt tell our Fameliſtical dreamers, that we muſt mortifie by the Spirit; they muſt not think to have theſe ſhowres of grace, and glory fall into their laps, while they ſit ſtill with a ſoulded hand. For the getting of the Spirit we muſt at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend on God in his Ordinances. Though the Miller cannot make a wind, yet he may ſet up his ſailes, and turn them into the wind. When we have received the Spirir, we are the inſtruments of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, yet not paſſive ones, but as ſervants, that work by the direction of their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, as the body works being enabled by the ſoul. We are not ſaved altogether, as we were created. <hi>He made us, not we our ſelves;</hi> ſo he ſaveth us, not we our ſelves; that is, as of our ſelves; but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing enabled by his Spirit: and thus, though it be true, that he works in us both the will and the deed; yet it is as true, that we muſt work out our own ſalvation. A ſilly Countrey-fellow once bought <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheus</hi> his harp, and thought it would make melody of it ſelf, without the touch of a skilful hand: ſo do theſe men think of the Spirit, that it will work in them, though
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:170192:44"/>they be idle, reſiſt, or quench the Spirit, and <hi>turn the grace of God into wantonneſſe,</hi> thus making God the cauſe of their ſins, if not an efficient, at leaſt a deficient; and they think they have done as much good, and omitted as much evil, as God by his grace enabled them.</p>
            <p>I muſt tell our ſuperſtitious <hi>Baalites,</hi> that this mortification, <hi>Non fit per diſciplinam Monaſticam, aut Baaliticam lanienam corporis, ſed per Spiritum reſiſtentem operibus carnis;</hi> is not done by Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſtical diſcipline, or by Baalitical cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the body, but by the Spirit op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing, and reſiſting the deeds of the body. Though a man faſt till he faint and dye, cover himſelf with ſackcloth day and night; though he beat himſelf black and blue, endure heat, and cold as much as the body will bear, not ſuffer their eyes to ſleep, or eye-lids to ſlumber; it's not their ſolitary caves, or tedious pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages; many that do ſo nouriſh pride, vain-glory, ſelf-confidence; but it's the Spirit of God, and yet the Spirit uſeth other inſtruments. The Word of God as a two edged-ſword, cuts the throat of our corruptions; in prayer we lay them open to God; preſſe him with his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:170192:45"/>and get grace and aſſiſtance from him, in voluntary chaſtning; our ſelves ordinari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, by ſobriety in meat, drink, apparel, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creation; extraordinarily, by prayer, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting, weeping: we do as it were with Gods plough ſoften our hard hearts, and ſo extinguiſh this fire, by withholding com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſtible matter, or by thoſe that are im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed by God. In the former we take up our croſſe, in this it's laid upon us. In the one we turn without, in this with a bridle in our jawes: But the Spirit muſt diffuſe it ſelf through all theſe to make them ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectual; and without it theſe bodily exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes profit little, the fleſh will ſtill <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>calcitrare,</hi> &amp; therefore Monaſticks, and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chorites have found corruption as ſtrong in the Cloyſter, as in the Court; in the Cell, as in the City. He that will not humble his body, cannot, will not humble his ſoul; but he that humbleth his body without the ſoul, loſeth his labour.</p>
            <p>Yea,<note place="margin">For Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation.</note> with your good leave I muſt tell the beſt man here, that it is not enough that he hath begun well, but he muſt go on. So the Apoſtle writes to converted <hi>Romans;</hi> ſo we ſpeak to converted Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, you have done it Sacramentally, make good your vow; you have done
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:170192:45"/>it in profeſſion, let your practice be anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable; you have done it really, but it's but in part, continue in well-doing. A good progreſſe and concluſion, is neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to life; as a good beginning. Take heed of beginning in the Spirit, and end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the fleſh. They that think they are mortified enough, muſt mortifie that proud conceit, or perhaps they will come ſhort of life. And for Cathariſts that boaſt of abſolute perfection, their reward ſhall be, they lead themſelves into a fools Paradiſe.</p>
            <p>By all this which hath been ſaid, we may verifie that of our Saviour, <hi>Matth.</hi> 6.14. Heaven it ſpued out the Angels that ſinned, and will not lick up the Devils vomit again.</p>
            <p>But though it be difficult, yet not impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, therefore I would not diſcourage any. It's eaſie to a ſpiritual man, and me thinks the benefit ſhould take away the difficulty; <hi>Look unto Jeſus the Author and finiſher of our faith.</hi> But alas, theſe joyes are farre off, and ſerve but little, or elſe the taſte of the world ſpoiles our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh. Our teeth are ſo ſet on edge with theſe apples of <hi>Sodom,</hi> that we cannot taſte the fruit of the tree of life.</p>
            <pb n="84" facs="tcp:170192:46"/>
            <p>See what there is in the Text to encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage us. 1. It's but the deeds of the body to be mortified, thoſe which we may well ſpare; God commands us not to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy any faculty of the ſoul, either to hurt the underſtanding, or dull the apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, or overload the memory, or clog the conſcience; not to kill the body, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume the ſpirits, by a dull, auſtere melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choly, not to deſtroy the forme or feature of it Religion it depriveth us of nothing that brings true pleaſure or profit. <hi>Adam</hi> in innocency, glorified Saints and Angels, God himſelf hath tranſcendent happineſſe, to which nothing can be added; yet it's the unhappineſſe of ſome to think they cannot be merry, unleſſe they are mad, nor happy except ſinful; that mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification abridgeth them of true delight. Again, theſe muſt but be mortified, not ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly aboliſhed. We cannot aboliſh them, to have no being, but onely mortifie them, that they do not reign; ſo that while ſin doth not prevail, but thou groaneſt under the reliques of corruption, God will accept thee, and that thou mayeſt do this, he gives thee his own Spirit to enable thee to the work, &amp; offers thee a Crown of glory at the end of thy labour. Surely if he had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:170192:46"/>thee a greater matter upon ſuch termes, wouldſt thou not have done it?</p>
            <p>What remaineth then, but that we ſet about the work chearfully. I exhort you all to be happy. The fulneſſe of glory will anſwer all the difficulties. I can ſay no more; <hi>Mortifie,</hi> and you <hi>ſhall live.</hi> If you will not kill, you muſt be killed. God hath proclaimed theſe deeds Traytors; they have ſhed the blood of Chriſt, done all the miſchief in the world, and, in a word, will undo our ſoules. How can we but with indignation ſee ſtrumpets more care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to adorne their bodies then we our ſoules! St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> mournes to ſee <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius</hi> take more paines to go to hell, then he could do to go to heaven. How can we endure to ſee a Papiſt take more paines to ſcourge his body, an earth-worme mace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate himſelfe to get wealth, an adulterer dance attendance to fulfil his luſt, and yet in the mean time we do nothing to get to heaven!</p>
            <p>Go home then with ſhame in thy countenance, faſting, weeping, and mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; with anger, indignation, and holy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge, looke on that heart of thine that hath offered ſuch indignity to heaven; by an holy Anathema deliver that fleſh of
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:170192:47"/>thine to Satan, ſmite on thy thigh with <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraim,</hi> on thy breaſt with the <hi>Publican,</hi> weep with <hi>David</hi> rivers of tears becauſe others keep not Gods Law, and weep bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly with <hi>Peter</hi> for denying thy Lord. Make a bath of tears with <hi>Mary</hi> for enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining ſo many Devils in thine heart; for get a while to eate thy bread, &amp; by faſting, and abſtinence be revenged on thy ſelfe for ſin paſt, and keep under thy body for time to come. It's one of the nailes that crucifies the fleſh, and a meanes to take down the rankneſſe of this fertile field, <hi>ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulare putatis aratrum.</hi> But if thou canſt not weep, and command tears, at leaſt get that <hi>dolorem appretiativum.</hi> Value your ſins at ſuch a rate, that they deſerve tears of blood. Wiſh that thy head were a foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, and thine eyes, as Conduit-pipes. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat God to accept the deſire for the deed, and the blood, and tears of Chriſt for all. But men now adayes can mortifie with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out renting the heart, faſting a day, ſhed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding a tear. But withall remember to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie too, elſe thy tears will be no better then <hi>Eſaus,</hi> thy faſting like <hi>Ahabs.</hi> Purge, not that thou mayeſt ſurfeit; repent not that thou mayeſt ſin; returne, not like the dog to the vomit; if thou do, thy latter end
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:170192:47"/>will be worſe then thy beginning. But bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed is the man that ſorrows, after a godly manner; for this works repentance <hi>never to be repented of. Bleſſed are they that mourne</hi> now, <hi>that ſowe in teares; for they ſhall reape in joy,</hi> they ſhall finde triumph in torment, joy in tribulation, refreſhing in faſting, life in death. <hi>Bern. Filii hujus ſeculi vident cruces noſtras, non conſolationes:</hi> The ſons of this world ſee our croſſes, but not our comforts. If any thing were better then life, God would not deny it you; he ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts you Martyrs in manner; <hi>Mortificare opera carnis genus Martyrii eſt, horrore quidem mitius, ſed diuturnitate moleſtius:</hi> To mortifie the deeds of the body, is a kinde of martyrdome, milder indeed in its horrour, but more troubleſome in its long continuance. Certainly they that keep ſuch a <hi>Lent,</hi> ſhall have a glorious <hi>Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> at the day of their reſurrection, <hi>when all teares ſhall be wiped from their eyes,</hi> and they ſhall remaine, and raigne with God in bliſſe for ever. And thus I have travelled through theſe Propoſitions in their abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute conſideration.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> We conſidered theſe words in their op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition. Here are two contrary wayes, that tend to two contrary ends. They cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſin themſelves that think to fare as well as
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:170192:48"/>the beſt,<note place="margin">The word conſidered in their op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition.</note> and yet ſin as bad as the worſt; and they fill themſelves with unneceſſary fears that live ſtrictly, and carefully, and yet comfort not themſelves in Gods promiſes.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It doth no whit prejudice the godly in their comfort, that God is ſo ſevere againſt the wicked; <hi>Cains</hi> profaneneſſe doth not hurt <hi>Abel,</hi> he is accepted. Though <hi>Judas</hi> be a devil, the reſt fare not the worſe. So at the laſt day while the wicked wiſh the hils, and mountains to cover them, the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly lift up their heads. <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Moſes</hi> make uſe of their intereſt with God, even when he is provoked againſt <hi>Sodom,</hi> and <hi>Jaſrel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The wicked are not priviledged by Gods mercies on the godly, as we ſee in the Wiſe and Fooliſh Virgins. Gods mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, Chriſts merits, the precious promiſes and priviledges of the Goſpel availe them nothing. Gods mercies are limited to cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine conditions, therefore let not wicked men boulſter up themſelves in theſe, heed not lying vanities.</p>
            <p>We conſider them in their coherence. Therefore we ſhould mortifie ſin,<note n="3" place="margin">And in their co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herence.</note> becauſe if we live after the fleſh, we ſhall die.</p>
            <p>It's not abſurd to propound life and death as Motives to obedience. God did ſo to <hi>Adam</hi> in Paradiſe.</p>
            <pb n="89" facs="tcp:170192:48"/>
            <p>Yea, to men already converted, our Saviour doth ſo, <hi>Feare not him that can kill the body, &amp;c.</hi> So the Father at banquets would talke of hell, to keep men from ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. So the Apoſtle here to men already converted, <hi>If ye live, &amp;c.</hi> The meditation of death is not unprofitable for them. They are not out of danger of Gun-ſhot; though they are in a Cittadel, or ſtrong Tower, yet they have ſome fleſh, and are ſubject to ſpiritual ſecurity, preſumption, or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneneſſe. The Tower cannot be demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed, but they may looke out at the win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes, and battlements, and be wounded.</p>
            <p>Hence we may conclude, that a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an may take comfort in an holy life. Here is an Antidote againſt Preſumption, and Deſpaire. None can preſume, but they that mortifie; and that is not preſumption, but hope; none can deſpaire, but ſuch as live af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the fleſh; and that is a feare upon good grounds.</p>
            <p>And now to draw to a concluſion.<note place="margin">The agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment 'twixt <hi>Armin.</hi> and their ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries in the rules of practiſe.</note> How happily might theſe two Propoſitions put an end to our unhappy controverſies, were men of peaceable ſpirits. The <hi>Areopagites</hi> in <hi>Athens</hi> in a doubtful caſe wherein they were loath to paſſe ſentence, differred it <hi>in diem longiſſimum,</hi> it may be for an hundred
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:170192:49"/>years. I would to God we could do ſo in theſe that I am ſure are doubtful, but this is to ſuſpend men in a Neutrality to beleeve nothing. S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> anſwers ſome well, that would not beleeve, unleſſe all objections were cleared: <hi>Sunt innumera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biles objectiones quae non ſunt finiendae ante fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem, ne finiatur vita ſine fide:</hi> There are innumerable objections which muſt not be diſpatched and anſwered before faith, &amp;c. Moderation in theſe myſteries is to be ſhewen, if any where. <hi>Neutram partem affirmantes, ſive deſtrueren tes, ſed tantum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modo ab audaci affirmandi praeſumptione re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocantes:</hi> Affirming, or denying neither of the two, but onely reſtraining us from bold preſumption in taking either part. But now every novice can determine in theſe things, when the wiſeſt men demurre, and can as ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly chalke out Gods ſecret wayes, as if with S. <hi>Paul</hi> they had been rapt up into the third heaven, and taken a tranſcript of the book of life. Either ſide is confident, and it may be in concluſion it will prove neither ſo nor ſo, and ſo it comes to paſſe, that religion is turned into nicities and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, bearing things certaine, and faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ening upon uncertaine, like <hi>Zeuxes,</hi> that pictured an old woman ſo to the life, that
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:170192:49"/>he laughed to death at the veiw of her.</p>
            <p>So I thinke our gracious Soveraigne hath taken a Religious and Wiſe courſe to ſilence theſe controverſies, more fit for Schooles then Pulpits, or rather fitter for heavens perfection then for earthly frailty to determine; <hi>Et Elias quum venerit ſolvet haec dubia.</hi> If I ſhould enter upon the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies, I ſhould contradict authority; or if I might, I would not ſo far preſume upon mine own weakneſſe; or if I had abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, and liberty, I durſt not ſo far abuſe your patience. Onely let me adviſe all, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially the unlearned, which with much ſtudy cannot ſo much as attaine the ſtating of the queſtions, to turne their cavilling a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Theory into Practice. Surely there is no ſuch vaſt difference in the points as they are handled by moderate men on both ſides, whatſoever ſome ſay, that ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther know not what they ſpeak, or will not know. But howſoever it is in the Theory, unleſſe I much miſtake, both ſides meet in the Practice.</p>
            <p>If any man ſhould aske me concerning the decree of election and reprobation,<note place="margin">Predeſtina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> here is a counterpane of it in my text. I will not ſay this is Gods whole decree, I dare ſay no ſecret decree contradicts it. We
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:170192:50"/>need not climbe up into heaven then to ſee whether God ſmile or frowne, nor wreſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen his Cabinet to ſee what ſecrets are there. Things revealed belong to us; if our names be written here, then infallibly are they there. If we finde them not here, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainely they are not there. I ſay then, leave diſputing about election, and labour to make your calling and election ſure. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin at the bottome of the ladder, and adde to your faith vertue, and to vertue know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and to knowledge temperance, &amp;c. Thus our Saviour ſtifles ſuch a controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, Maſter, ſhall many be ſaved? Strive to enter in at the ſtrait gate. But what ſhall this man do? Follow thou me. Let no man comfort himſelfe with any illuſion, or affright himſelfe with any fatall deſtiny. <hi>If ye live after, &amp;c.</hi> This is Gods Word, and by this we muſt be judged at the laſt day.</p>
            <p>For the ſecond Controverſie, Whether Redemption be univerſal; I ſay to that man Though Chriſt died for all men, as one ſide affirm, yet if thou live after the fleſh thou ſhalt dye, notwithſtanding the purchaſe of ſo precious a redemption, ſufficient in it ſelf, though not effectual unto thee through thine own perverſeneſſe; or if but for ſome few, as the other ſide affirm, if thou mortify
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:170192:50"/>the deeds of the body, thou art one that ſhall ſurely live.</p>
            <p>For the third, and fourth,<note place="margin">The man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving grace.</note> the manner of receiving grace. One ſide ſay, it doth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibly, and neceſſarily work at ſuch a time, and not before; the other, that through our perverſeneſſe we may turn the <hi>grace of God into wantonneſſe.</hi> Both agree in this; that a man may be ſaved, grace muſt be received and improved. The Spirit is the principal cauſe, but we muſt co-operate. We are not able of our ſelves to think a good thought; our ſufficiency is from him. Hence St. <hi>Paul,</hi> I live; yet that he might not ſeem to uſurp any of the honour, checks himſelf, yet not I. So we ſay, We muſt mortify, yet not we, but the Spirit; not we as the principal cauſe, but the Spirit; not the Spirit as the ſolitary cauſe, but we by the Spirit; let us look to it that the work be done, and then we ſhall not miſcarry.</p>
            <p>For the laſt, which is perſeverance; one ſide ſaith, we ſhall infalliblly ſtand,<note place="margin">Perſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance.</note> and as poſſible for Chriſt to fall out of heaven, as a Saint from Chriſt; the other ſide, that God will not forſake us, unleſſe we forſake him; and gives us grace ſufficient that we may not fall; but doth not ſo infallibly hold us up, but we may fall. Both ſides affirm
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:170192:51"/>perſeverance to be neceſſary unto life, and the conſcionable uſe of means to perſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance. Take heed then that there be not in any of you at any time an evil heart of unbelief to depart from the living God; and that this may never befal thee, put on the whole armour of God, that thou may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt ſtand in the evil day. Thus the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18. juſtifies God in his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings, and makes the people wary. So the Apoſtle writing here to Saints; and if any of you whom in charity I judge to be converted would hear any thing from me concerning perſeverance, I will anſwer you in the words of my text; <hi>If ye live after,</hi> &amp;c. Thus if a man in a modeſt humility, receive the known truth in the love of it, and ſo love it as to practiſe it, his end ſhall certainly be bleſſed.</p>
            <p>And now behold,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 30.15 The Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion.</note> this day I have ſet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you life and death, good and evil, bleſſing and curſing. There are but two eſtates in this life, and two after, propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionably. Some here walk after the fleſh, but they ſhall dye; the delight is preſent, but momentany; the pain is future, but eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal; ſome here by the Spirit mortify the deeds of the body, and they ſhall live here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aftes. The task here is ſharp, and preſent,
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:170192:51"/>but momentany; the reward future, but glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious and eternal. Were it not for that which followes, <hi>Ye ſhall dye,</hi> it were a brave thing to live after the fleſh; were it not for that which followes, <hi>Ye ſhall live,</hi> nothing more tedious then to mortify the deeds of the body. Wiſdome now will ſoon deride the controverſie, and pitch up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on her choice and inheritance ſo glorious ſo durable, though it be future; and the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance ſo difficult is to be preferred to a life of ſinne, though it had in it never ſo much pleaſure or profit, being momen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tany, and ſeconded with eternal wo. It's the fools voice, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Give me to day, take to morrow to thy ſelf. But if notwithſtanding what hath been ſaid, he ſhall ſtill walk in the waies of his own heart, all the curſes in Gods book ſhall fall on him. God will blot out his name from under heaven, and in heaven out of the book of life, ſo that in no place he ſhall be found but in hell. But every man here ſeems to chooſe life, in that he comes to hear that Goſpel, which is the Word of life. Oh they make it not the ſavor of death to death. Labour then by the Spirit to mortify the deeds of the body ſo ſhall you live many <hi>Halcion</hi> daies here upon
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:170192:52"/>earth, and when you dye, the Angels ſhall carry your ſoules into Paradiſe, while your bodies repoſe themſelves in their graves, as a bed of down, till the Lord of Glory ſhall return to judg both quick and dead, where the body being raiſed and reunited to the ſoul, both ſoul and body ſhall live in the perpetual viſion and fruition of God. To which glory he for his mercy bring us, who hath ſo dearly bought us, even Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>the Author and finiſher of our faith:</hi> To whom with the Father, and the bleſſed Spirit be aſcribed all, honour, glory, praiſe, thankſgiving and obedience from this time forth and for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
